<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods great care of his good people in bad times discovered in several sermons / preached by Mr. James Nalton (late minister of St. Leonards Foster-Lane) immediately upon his return from Holland, about twelve years since ; published by J.F., teacher of short- writing, who took them in characters from the said Mr. J. Nalton.</title>
            <author>Nalton, James, 1600-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N122A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282174</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282174</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150135</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89716)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150135)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2233:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods great care of his good people in bad times discovered in several sermons / preached by Mr. James Nalton (late minister of St. Leonards Foster-Lane) immediately upon his return from Holland, about twelve years since ; published by J.F., teacher of short- writing, who took them in characters from the said Mr. J. Nalton.</title>
                  <author>Nalton, James, 1600-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 160 p., [1] leaf of plates : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Nathanael Webb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXV [1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 160.</note>
                  <note>Includes frontispiece port. of author.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Providence and government of God.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:150135:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150135:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Portraiture of the Reuerent M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Ja<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nalton Late Preacher at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Le<hi rend="sup">o</hi>nards Foster lane<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </head>
                  <figDesc>portrait of James Nalton</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150135:2"/>
            <p>GODS Great care of his GOOD PEOPLE IN BAD TIMES.</p>
            <p>Diſcovered in ſeveral SERMONS Preached by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>JAMES NALTON</hi> (Late Miniſter of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Leonards Foſter-Lane</hi>) immediately upon his return out of <hi>Holland</hi> about Twelve years ſince.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by <hi>J. F.</hi> Teacher of Short-Writing, who took them in Characters from the ſaid M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>J. Nalton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 8.28.</hi>
               </bibl> And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Webb</hi> at the Royal Oake near the Little North-Door of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls.</hi> M.DC.LXV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:150135:3"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Royall Oake</head>
                  <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150135:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Shall give thee onely this brief account of theſe Sermons and of their Authour. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>James Nalton,</hi> who was whileſt he lived a painfull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in the Lords vineyard, and now (I doubt not) a bleſſed Saint in Heaven, there reaping
<pb facs="tcp:150135:4"/>the fruits of his labours: Being about twelve years ſince lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with an evil eye by ſome then in power, did (by advice of friends) prudently withdraw himſelf for a time into <hi>Holland,</hi> to avoid impending dangers. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately upon his return unto <hi>London</hi> he preached theſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, being as 'tis very probable ſome of the fruits of his ſtudies whileſt in another Country: his chief ſcope and deſign in them is, to ſet forth Gods ſingular care of his own people in ſad and ſinfull times. How well this hath been performed by him, and how pious and practical, and in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects very uſefull theſe Sermons are, I had much rather the Reader ſhould finde by his own peruſal, than be informed by any thing that I can ſay of them. And let me adde this for his encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that I have not here pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb facs="tcp:150135:4"/>onely ſome ſhreds and frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Sermons, as hath been the too common (though not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable) practiſe of ſome (and thoſe alſo ſo moulded and model'd by them, that very little either of the method or ſtile of thoſe whoſe Works they have pretended to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh could be diſcerned in them) theſe Sermons being here preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the view of the Reader ſo as delivered by the Authour, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely a paring off of ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, which though they may have their good uſe in preaching, yet not ſo in printing, preaching and printing very much differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; not but that the Reader may poſsibly eſpy ſome faults in theſe Sermons (though I preſume none very material) which if he ſhould, I have onely this juſt requeſt to make to him, that he would (as there is great reaſon he ſhould)
<pb facs="tcp:150135:5"/>impute them to the Tranſcriber or Printer, but not to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150135:5"/>
            <head>GODS great care of his good People in bad Times.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jeremiah Chap. 24. Verſe 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, the God of Iſrael, Like theſe good Figs, ſo will Lacknowledge them that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away captive of Judah, whom I have ſent out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are part of a Viſion which the Prophet ſaw, concerning <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> The time when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſaw this Viſion, appears in the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150135:6"/>firſt Verſe of this Chapter, to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had carried away <hi>Jeconiah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Princes, and a great multitude with them into <hi>Babylon.</hi> The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this Viſion was this, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to comfort and ſupport the faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drooping ſpirits of theſe poor captives, who becauſe they ſaw ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their brethren left in the Land of <hi>Judah,</hi> enjoying their liberty and their inheritances, when themſelves were now under captivity, diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſtript of all their enjoyments, and caſt into a ſtrange Land, were hereupon exceedingly diſcouraged, and began to have their hearts ſink in deſpondency and deſpair: God now by this Viſion of two Baskets, one of good Figs, and another of bad Figs, would let them ſee, that however in the eye of ſenſe, thoſe that were left in the Land of <hi>Judah</hi> ſeemed to be more happy, and thoſe that were carried captive into <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſeemed to be more miſerable; yet thoſe that were left in the Land of <hi>Judah</hi> were bad Figs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God would ſend <hi>the ſword, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150135:6"/>famine, and the peſtilence amongst them, that ſhould conſume them from off the good Land;</hi> their end would be very miſerable, as it is in the laſt Verſe of the Chapter. And on the contrary, though they that were carried away captive ſeemed to be very miſerable for the preſent, yet they were the good Figs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their end would be very bleſſed, according to the words that I have now read unto you; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, the God of Iſrael, Like theſe good Figs, ſo will I acknowledge them that are carried away captive of Judah, whom I have ſent out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Text then there are theſe two branches obſervable;
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, We have the Author of a comfortable Meſſage.</item>
                  <item>And ſecondly, We have the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage it ſelf.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the comfortable Meſſage is the Lord; who is deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed here by the intereſt he had in, and the relation he had unto his people; he is called <hi>the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150135:7"/>Secondly, We have the Meſſage it ſelf. And herein take notice of two particulars;
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, The explication of a Type.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, The application of it to theſe poor captives.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The explication of a Type in theſe words, <hi>Like theſe good Figs;</hi> by which the Lord ſhews the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> what was meant by the Basket of good Figs.</p>
            <p>And then we have the application of this Type to theſe poor captives; and the application is wholly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and the comfort it yeelds conſiſts in three particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, God doth here promiſe them, that he would <hi>acknowledge them,</hi> and own them in a ſtrange Land.</item>
               <item>Secondly, The Lord tells them that he himſelf did ſend them into the Land of the <hi>Caldeans.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And thirdly, He doth aſſure them that this tranſportation or carrying into Captivity, ſhould be for their profit and advantage: <hi>I have ſent them out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:150135:7"/>We will begin with the firſt branch of the Text, and that is the Author of this comfortable Meſſage, <hi>the Lord;</hi> deſcribed here by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation unto his people, he is called <hi>the God of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here it may be demanded, Why doth God ſtile himſelf by the name of <hi>the God of Iſrael,</hi> in this comfortable Meſſage that he ſends to theſe poor captives?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, He doth it for this end, namely, to let them know, that though he ſeemed to caſt them off from being his people, becauſe he had now ſuffered them to be carried captive into a ſtrange Land, yet he was the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſtill, and that they were even then under his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care, and he had a tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard unto them.</p>
            <p>The Obſervation then which I would commend to you from hence, (that God calls himſelf <hi>the God of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> even at this time when <hi>Iſrael</hi> was carried into captivity) is this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God doth not caſt off his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>even then when he ſeems to caſt them off.—God is not regardleſs of his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150135:8"/>people, when he ſeems to be regardleſs of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prove this Doctrine to you, there are theſe two branches that I muſt make plain:</p>
            <p>Firſt, That God doth ſometimes ſeemingly caſt off his people.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, That God doth not, will not, cannot, really caſt them off.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I muſt prove that God doth ſometimes ſeemingly caſt off his people. He ſometimes ſeems to be ſo regardleſs of them, and of their condition, as if he had ſet them at a ſad diſtance from his love. Thus it was with theſe poor captives here in the Text, that were carried away into <hi>Babylon</hi> with King <hi>Jeconiah,</hi> and the Princes. And thus you ſhall ſee the Church complains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Why ſtandeſt thou afar off O Lord, why hideſt thou thy ſelf in times of trouble?</hi> And thus <hi>David</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.1. <hi>How long wilt thou forget me O Lord for ever, how long wilt thou hide thy face from me?</hi> And thus <hi>Job</hi> complains, <hi>Job</hi> 13.24. <hi>Wherefore hideſt thou thy face, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150135:8"/>holdeſt me for thy enemy.</hi> And thus the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> complains, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. v. 8, and 44. <hi>Alſo when I cry and ſhout he ſhutteth out my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and thou haſt covered thy ſelf with a cloud that our prayer ſhould not paſs through.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you may ſay, Why doth God ſometimes ſeem to caſt off his own people?</p>
            <p>I anſwer: He doth it for theſe reaſons:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> God would hereby teach us to live by faith, and not by fight and ſence onely: if there were no tryals, if there were no deſertions nor temptations, there would be no exerciſe of faith at all: but now when a people can againſt hope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve in hope, that is, againſt hope of ſence, can believe in hope of the Promiſes, and can depend upon God at that time when he ſeems to caſt them off, and can hang upon the Promiſes as the earth is ſaid to hang upon nothing, this is the life,<note place="margin">Job 26.7.</note> this is the efficacie of faith indeed.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, God doth it,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> to teach his people to reflect upon and be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150135:9"/>ſenſible of their unkindneſs in turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their backs upon him, and that therefore it were juſt with him to turn his back upon them for ever.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> God doth it for this end, to teach his people how to prize his preſence at a higher rate, that he may indeer the mercy of his perpetual abode: impriſonment makes liberty ſo much the ſweeter, and war (we know) makes peace ſo much the ſweeter; and health is moſt wellcome when it brings with it recommendation from ſickneſs. If it were with us as it is in <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or with thoſe that live farre Northward, that we ſhould enjoy the light of the Sunne but onely for five or ſix moneths in the year, how welcome would the Sunne be to us then: ſo Gods hiding away his face ſometimes, makes his preſence the ſweeter and the more welcome to us.</item>
                  <item>And then fourthly,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſeems to deſert his people, that they may not deſert him; for ſhould we alwayes enjoy the ſmiles of his face, we ſhould quickly grow
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150135:9"/>proud and wanton, and ſhould ceaſe to ſeek him ſo early as otherwiſe we would do; and therefore God deals with us as the Nurſe doth that hideth her ſelf from her Childe, to make the Childe cry after her; ſo God ſometimes leaves us, that we may ſeek him the more earneſtly, and follow him the more cloſely. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>I will goe and return to my place</hi> (ſaies God) <hi>till they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their offences and ſeek my face, in their affliction they will ſeek me early.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort conſiſts in communion with God; for if he hide his face from us the ſteps of our ſtrength are ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; but yet this is as true, that while we live here upon earth, we can never enjoy a full and conſtant communion with our God, becauſe there is a mixture of corruption with grace. We are in a mixt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition here below, it is neither night nor day with us,<note place="margin">Zech. 14.6.</note> but partly night and partly day, and as long as we are in a mixt condition, ſo long we have need of a mixt manifeſtation.</item>
                  <item>Fifthly and laſtly,<label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>5</label> God doth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150135:10"/>ſometimes ſeemingly caſt off his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and doth deſert us that he may not deſert us; I mean God doth ſometimes deſert us in our temporal comforts, that he may not deſert us in our ſpiritual comforts; and God ſometimes deſerts us in our ſpiritual comforts, that he may not deſert us in our ſpiritual graces; and he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts us ſometimes in one grace, that he may not deſert us in another grace; as for example, God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deſerts us in prayer, that he may ſtrengthen the grace of humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: in a word, God deſerts us for a while, that he may not deſert us for ever; God deſerts us in a little wrath, that he may not deſert us in everlaſting wrath, that wrath that burns in hell to all eternity. Thus you have the firſt branch of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine opened to you, <hi>That God doth ſometimes ſeemingly caſt off his people.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But now ſecondly, <hi>God doth not, will not really caſt off his people;</hi> though they may be ſometimes caſt down, yet they are never caſt off; and though they may be dejected,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150135:10"/>yet they ſhall never be rejected; and though they may be left for a while, yet they ſhall never be caſt away. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.8, 9. <hi>But thou art Iſrael my ſervant, Jacob whom I have choſen, I have choſen thee and not caſt thee away.</hi> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.21. <hi>Remember theſe O Jacob and Iſrael, for thou art my ſervant I have formed thee, thou art my ſervant O Iſrael thou ſhalt not be forgotten of me.</hi> True indeed, the righteous, that is Gods own people may ſometimes ſay, <hi>the Lord hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me,</hi> as it is <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.14. But ſee what God anſwers, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16. <hi>Can a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man forget her ſucking Childe, that ſhe ſhould not have compaſſion on the ſon of her womb, yea they may forget, yet will not I forget thee; behold I have graven thee upon the palms of my hands, thy walls are continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</hi> Take but one Scripture more, and it is a full Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.36, 37. <hi>If thoſe ordinances</hi> (of the Sun, Moon, and Stars) <hi>can depart from before me ſaith the Lord, then the ſeed of Iſrael alſo ſhall ceaſe from being a nation before me for ever:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150135:11"/>Thus ſaith the Lord, if heaven above can be meaſured, and the foundations of the earth be ſearched out beneath, I will alſo caſt off all the ſeed of Iſrael for all that they have done ſaith the Lord:</hi> But that can never be, the ordinances can never be changed, (ſaith God) therefore I will never caſt off my People. And would you know the reaſons of this ſecond branch of the doctrine, I ſhall give you theſe four briefly.</p>
            <p>The firſt is drawn from the immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability of Gods Councel,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of God ſtandeth ſure, having this ſeal, the Lord knoweth them that are his.</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19. Gods great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, the councel he had in his boſom before the world began, it was to ſave his Elect. Now ſaith God, my councel ſhall ſtand.</p>
            <p>The ſecond may be drawn from the unchangeableneſs of his love; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>I have loved thee</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>with an everlaſting love,</hi> Jerem. 31.3. <hi>and the gifts, and calling of God are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repentance,</hi> Rom. 11.29. He ſpeaks of thoſe gifts that flow from election and from effectual calling,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150135:11"/>theſe gifts God never repents of, though he may repent of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gifts he beſtows upon hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</p>
            <p>But here it may be objected; May not the ſins of Gods own people cauſe him ſometimes to repent?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, No. True indeed the ſins of Gods people may hinder the manifeſtation and the diſcoveries of his love, and may cauſe a fatherly diſpleaſure in him towards them, but they cannot utterly take away his love: as the undutifullneſs of a ſon to his father, may cauſe his father to hide his face from him, but yet he doth not diſinherit him or caſt him off: as all our ſins when they were laid upon Chriſts back, could not take away Gods love from him then, ſo neither ſhall they take away his love from us now, eſpecially when by the blood of his ſon they are purged away.</p>
            <p>The third Reaſon may be drawn from the ſtedfaſtneſs of Gods Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> and the Promiſes wrapt up in it. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. <hi>Although my houſe be not ſo with God:</hi> though my
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150135:12"/>family hath not been rightly order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and though my politicall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hath had many failings in it as I have been a King and a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, <hi>yet</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) <hi>he hath made with me an everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ordered in all things, and ſure, for this is all my ſalvation, and all my deſire, although he make it not to grow:</hi> though I ſhould break Covenant with God, God will not break Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with me:<note place="margin">Hebr. 10.23.</note> God (you muſt know) is free in promiſing and faithfull in performing, <hi>and if we believe not, yet he abideth faithfull, he cannot deny himſelf,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.13. God can as ſoon ceaſe to be God as ceaſe to be a faithfull God; it is an act of mercy in God to promiſe, but having promiſed, 'tis then an act of juſtice for God to performe what he hath promiſed.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God works the heart of his people ſo that they ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here and cleave to him, and not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him: now where God ſees a poor ſinner unwilling to forſake him, God is as unwilling to forſake the ſinner: What (ſaith God) wilt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150135:12"/>thou keep cloſe to me, and cleave to me ſtill, and hang upon me though I ſeem to caſt thee off, why then if thou doeſt thus cleave to me I will cleave to thee, <hi>I will never leave thee nor forſake thee,</hi> Heb. 13.5. In which place, it is well obſerved, there are no leſs than five negatives,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>I will not, I will not, I will not, I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, never leave thee nor forſake thee.</hi> So you ſee now the Point proved to you in both the branches of it; Firſt, <hi>That God doth ſometimes ſeemingly caſt off his people.</hi> But ſecondly, <hi>He never doth, he never can really caſt them off.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the Uſe of this Point:</p>
            <p>Firſt,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> By way of Inſtruction or Admonition it ſhould teach us this leſſon, namely, to learn to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, and not to be ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the manner of Gods deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings towards his own Children; take heed of entertaining hard thoughts of God, though thou maiſt be under ſtreights and preſſures, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, outward, inward temptations and deſertions, or outward affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and miſeries, yet take heed of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150135:13"/>murmuring againſt God, yea though he ſeem for a while, to hide his face from thee, it is true indeed we ſhould be very ſenſible of the leaſt frown of our fathers face, and of the leaſt of his withdrawings from us, as <hi>David</hi> in the like caſe Pſalm. 30.7. <hi>Thou didſt hide thy face</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and I was troubled</hi> look as it is with a little Child that hath loſt its Mother in the fields, it cryes, and lifts up its note, my Mother, my Mother, ſo much more when God is gone, ſhould we cry out, alas, where is my God, O! where is my Lord, how ſhall I meet with him, whom my ſoul loveth, for if God be gone, light is gone, life is gone; yea, hope, joy, peace and all is gone; therefore we ſhould be ſenſible (I ſay) of Gods withdrawings from us: I but yet not ſo ſenſible as to deſpair, and to ſink down in deſpondency, for God will come, and mercy will come, Peace and joy will come, yea Chriſt and comfort will come; as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Glover</hi> the Martyr, he found no comfort, till he came to the Stake, and then he cryed out, <hi>O he is come, he is come,</hi> meaning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150135:13"/>the Holy Ghoſt was come: the long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt night will have its day, and though ſorrow may be for a night, yet joy will come in the morning, therefore believe and wait, ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 40.1. <hi>In waiting I have waited, and mine eyes fail while I wait for my God,</hi> Pſal. 69.3. And pray and wait, and lie at the feet of mercy and wait, and be humble and wait, for certainly they that wait upon God ſhall never be aſhamed of their waiting. That is the firſt Uſe for Information.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Here is matter for Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation to all or moſt of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, I may ſpeak (I am afraid) not only my own heart, but the hearts of many of you here preſent; what cauſe have we to be humbled for our unbelief, and our diſtruſt of Gods power, and providence, and promiſes? if we are in any ſtreights, O how ready are we to cry out, <hi>the Lord hath forſaken me, &amp; my Lord hath forgotten me; and 'tis in vain to wait upon God any longer:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 49.14.</note> truely theſe are the murmurings and complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our hearts: we are very apt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150135:14"/>to be ſuſpitious of God, and to have hard thoughts of our Father, to be jealous that God will not be as good as his word: we queſtion his truth and faithfullneſs; we can truſt him for our eternal, but not for our temporal deliverance: the truth is we are ſhort ſpirited and loath to wait; <hi>he that believes makes not haſte,</hi> but we have ſo little faith, that we make haſte, and are ready to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the holy One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> we are very unwilling to truſt God, unleſs we can trace him; for this we ſhould be humbled and aſhamed in the ſight of our God.</p>
            <p>But thirdly (and the Uſe which I principally aim at) for Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>3</label> two Exhortations of great importance I have to commend to you, (and then I ſhall cloſe up this Point onely with a word of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.)</p>
            <p>The firſt is this; If it be thus, that though God may ſometimes ſeem to caſt off his people, yet he doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver really caſt them off: Then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you make this ſure to your own ſouls, that you are of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150135:14"/>of Gods people, elſe you can have no comfort from this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for you ſee he is call'd here in the Text <hi>the God of Iſrael:</hi> be ſure you are <hi>Gods Iſrael,</hi> and then this Doctrine will afford you abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of comfort.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay to me, How ſhall we know and be aſſured that we are Gods people, and that God is our God, and will be our God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we are, and in what condition ſoever we are.</p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, Content not your ſelves with generals, that you are profeſſors of Religion, that you have the ſtile of Chriſtians, and the bare naked name of Chriſtianity, for you know what is ſaid of the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Rev. 3.1. <hi>Thou haſt a name that thou liveſt, and art dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As now firſt, do not content your ſelves that you are profeſſors of the Goſpel, when others are oppoſers of the Goſpel, for believe it, profeſſors of the Goſpel may periſh everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly. <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22.23. <hi>Many will ſay to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy name,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150135:15"/>and in thy name have caſt out Devils, and in thy name done many wonderfull works?</hi> have we not fat at thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, been admitted to the Sacrament, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> yet our bleſſed Saviour will ſay, <hi>Depart from me, I know you not,</hi> though you have been profeſſors.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, Content not your ſelves with this, that you frequent Ordinances, when others it may be deſpiſe them (and ſo from Scepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme turn to Atheiſme, as many do at this day) for you ſhall read of ſome <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31, 32. that did ſit before God like his people, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in hearing the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> and his Doctrine was to them as ſweet as muſick, <hi>they heard thee with delight</hi> (ſaith God to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet) <hi>and with their mouth they ſhew much love, but though they hear my words yet they will not do them, for their heart goeth after their cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs.</hi> It is not enough to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Ordinances, content not your ſelves therefore with that.</p>
            <p>Thirly, Content not your ſelves with this, that you are free from groſs and ſcandalous ſins: the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150135:15"/>
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.11. could ſay, <hi>God I thank thee that I am not as other men are, extortioners, unjuſt, adulterers, or even as this Publican.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Content not your ſelves with this, that you have bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts than other men; it may be thou haſt excellent gifts in prayer, thou haſt a voluble tongue, a fluent expreſſion of thy ſelf, and art enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with knowledge, and canſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute for the truth, O do not reſt fatisfied with this, for Chriſtianity is a matter of grace rather than of gifts, gifts are but the common work of Gods Spirit, and are many times, nay for the moſt part beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon caſtawayes; gifts are for others good more than for our own good, whereas grace proceeds from Gods peculiar love, and grace is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed for our own good more than for the good of others; remember this therefore, a man may go to hell notwithſtanding all his gifts.</p>
            <p>And fifthly, Do not content your ſelves that you are joyned with Gods people, and have the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of them that are godly, alas
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150135:16"/>godly men may be deceived, they may think a great deal better of you than there is cauſe; conſider what the Apoſtle ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Not he that commendeth himſelf is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but he whom the Lord commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> ſo may I ſay, not he that man commendeth is approved of God, but he whom God commendeth: there are not any of all theſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward priviledges of Gods people but an hypocrite may have them, and may go as farre in them as the moſt ſincere profeſſour in the world.</p>
            <p>But you may ſay, What ſhall I do that I may be aſſured that God is my God, and that I am one of his people whom he will not caſt off?</p>
            <p>Brethren, you muſt know that the enquiry muſt be made from within, from your own boſoms. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Let every man prove his own work, and then ſhall he have rejoycing in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone, and not in another.</hi> That is, as One comments well upon the Text, <hi>that a mans rejoycing may be in the teſtimony of his own conſcience, and not in the applauſe of another mans tongue:</hi> you muſt look I ſay from
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150135:16"/>within, that this your rejoycing be the teſtimony of a good conſcience; <hi>that you may have,</hi> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10 <hi>the witneſs in your ſelves:</hi> Conſider therefore what are the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctings of your ſouls towards God, and then you may know what Gods actings are towards you. Now the actings of your ſouls towards God, may be diſcerned and diſcovered by theſe ſix or ſeaven evidences, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you mark them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Tell me, can you chooſe God for your God, for your Lord and Maſter? can you chooſe to ſerve him, as well as to be juſtified and ſaved by him? Chriſts generation are call'd a ſeed that will ſerve him, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 22.30. <hi>a ſeed ſhall ſerve him, it ſhall be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Lord for a generation: a ſeed ſhall ſerve him:</hi> it is a good obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tuntur Deo ut ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do.</note> 
               <hi>The carnal man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>doth but make uſe of God that he may enjoy the world; I but on the contrary, a godly ſincere Chriſtian doth but make uſe of the world that he may enjoy God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again ſecondly, Ask your own ſouls this queſtion; who is your
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150135:17"/>Counſellor, or who do you conſult withall in the times of your doubts, and fears, and ſtreights, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; do you conſult with God, or do you conſult with fleſh and blood? This is the Churches argument, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 48.14. <hi>For this God is our God for ever and ever, he will be our guid even unto death.</hi> Now do you do thus, do you conſult with God, are you guid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Spirit, or are you guided by the ſpirit of the world:<note place="margin">Gal. 1.16.</note> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> would not conſul with fleſh and blood, do you conſult altogether with the world? thus and thus ſaith the world, thus and thus do I eſteem the world, why let the world and all the world be liars, and God onely true, he is to be conſulted with and not the world.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Ask your ſouls this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, What is your refuge, what is your ſupport in the day of your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and diſtreſſes, what do you moſt of all truſt to in the day of your calamity? <hi>Some truſt in chareots, and ſome in horſes, but we will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the name of the Lord our God,</hi> Pſal. 20.7. Some truſt in their wits,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150135:17"/>that is in their carnal policies, and in the ſhifts and fetches of their own brains; and ſome again truſt in their wealth, <hi>The rich mans wealth is his ſtrong City,</hi> Prov. 18.11. and ſome truſt in the favour of great men, whom <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaies,<note place="margin">Jer. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arme:</hi> and ſome truſt in one thing, and ſome in another, I but canſt thou ſay with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 71.3. <hi>Be thou my ſtrong habitation, whereunto I may continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſort:</hi> let others truſt in this and truſt in that, I but I will not truſt in my ſword, nor in my bow, neither in my wealth, nor wit, nor friends, nor in my carnal refuges, I regard none of theſe,<note place="margin">Pſ. 73.28.</note> but <hi>it is good for me to draw nigh to God,</hi> it is good for me to keep cloſe to God in wayes of righteouſneſs, if I keep my inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, my integrity will keep me; canſt thou thus make God thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge? That is a third evidence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou maiſt know thou art one of thoſe whom God will not caſt off.</p>
            <p>And then fourthly, Ask thy ſoul this queſtion, Who art thou willing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150135:18"/>ſhall be thy reward at the great day? canſt thou ſay my record is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and my reward alſo is in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.5.</note> 
               <hi>that though men render me evil for good, and hatred for my love, yet ſurely my judgment is with the Lord, and my work with my God,</hi> Iſa. 49.4. for it is obſerved, that the ſame He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word that ſignifies <hi>work,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies alſo <hi>a reward;</hi> and it is a good obſervation, that Gods work is our wages, it is reward enough for us to do ſervice for God: Now-canſt thou ſay, what reward ſoever I have here on earth, or what injury ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I meet with from men, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding I have my reward in Heaven; therefore if my enemy hunger I can feed him, if he thirſt I can give him drink, I can overcome evil with goodneſs, and all becauſe I have my reward in Heaven: But on the contrary, moſt miſerable is the condition of that man that hath his reward here on earth, and his portion here below: It is ſaid <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.2. <hi>The Phariſees have their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> all that ever they can look for, as the word ſignifies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:150135:18"/>But then fifthly, Ask thy ſoul this queſtion, Hath God the ſupremacy in thy heart, hath he the higheſt room, hath he the beſt room in thy ſoul? haſt thou ſet up a Throne for God in thy heart, whereas hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſelf-love and the creature have been ſet up above God, I but now whatever thou affecteſt or eſteemeſt, thou affecteſt and eſteemeſt it onely in order to God, and in him and for him; canſt thou ſay, I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved I will not hinder nor break my peace with God to keep peace with men, O God forbid I ſhould do ſo: as a common ſouldier doth not break the command of his Captain though he do not obey his Captain, if the Generall command the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, for the Generall muſt be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed though all the inferiour Officers be diſpleaſed: ſo here, God muſt be obeyed, his voice muſt be hearkned to, though all the world, and all the Princes of the world ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the contrary, Gods command muſt ſtand, it is a good rule— <hi>It is no prejudice to any humane authority, to prefer Gods authority
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150135:19"/>before it,</hi> for if to preſerve the deareſt enjoyment we have in the world, we break our peace with God, the Lord is able to daſh all the comfort, we expect from that enjoyment, and to make it either a dead content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or elſe a torment to us, that we ſhall have (as he ſaid) the gifts of God without God himſelf,<note place="margin">Bona Dei ſine boxo Deo.</note> we may have the ſhell of the mercy, but ſhall never have the kernell of the mercy: But on the contrary, if we keep our peace with God, we ſhall be ſure to find in him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we deny for him, riches, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, friends, liberty, comforts, or any thing, we ſhall have all in him, and all will be ſo much the ſweeter to us, as they ſpring from the Fountain, and are not convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us by the Ciſtern, as they were before. This is a fifth queſtion I propound to you, or an evidence whereby you may know whether you are Gods people: Can you thus ſet up a Throne for God in your hearts, that he ſhall have the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and his authority ſhall be obeyed, whoever be diſpleaſed, or diſobeyed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:150135:19"/>Sixthly, Can you be contented with God for your portion? (that is another evidence I would propound to you) that if you were to chooſe a thouſand times, you would chooſe no other God but him. Pſal. 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and there is none upon earth that I deſire beſides thee,</hi> nothing but thy ſelf O bleſſed God, can give ſatisfaction to my immortall ſoul; if I have but thee, though I be as poor as <hi>Job</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the dunghill, yet I am rich enough, I will ſay with <hi>David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 16.6.</note> 
               <hi>the lines are fallen unto me in pleaſant places, yea I have a goodly heritage,</hi> becauſe the Lord himſelf is my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Now if you can thus chooſe God; you may conclude that God hath choſen you; if you can thus love God, you may certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, tha God loves you; and if you are his people, you may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured he is your God, and will ever continue to be your God, that is the ſixth evidence.</p>
            <p>In the ſeventh and laſt place, Call your ſelves to an account, and ſee whether ye be Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea, or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150135:20"/>no, for you ſee God is the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God will not caſt off his people,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.21.</note> his <hi>Iſrael, thou art Iſrael, my ſervant, I will not caſt thee away;</hi> the place I named before,<note place="margin">Pſa. 73.1.</note> and <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is good to Iſrael, even to ſuch as are of a clean heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> and <hi>peace ſhall be upon the Iſrael of God.</hi> Tell me therefore are you true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> are you <hi>Nathanaels</hi> in whom there is no guile, can you turn the inſides of your Spirits out unto God, and ſay,<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>ſearch me O Lord, and know my heart, try me, and know my thoughts, and ſee if there be any way of wickedneſs in me.</hi> I cannot deny but there is wickedneſs in me, but ſee if there be any <hi>way</hi> of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, any <hi>courſe</hi> of ſin in me, ſo that I make a <hi>trade</hi> of ſin, he that is born of God doth not <hi>practiſe</hi> ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> 1.3, 9. he doth not ſay he doth not ſin at all, but he doth not make a <hi>Trade</hi> of ſin as the word ſignifies. Canſt thou ſay, Lord thou knoweſt, in the uprightneſs of my heart I ſpeak it, there is not one Duty, but I would ſubmit to it, and would willingly practiſe it; there is not one
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150135:20"/>ſin that I allow in me, I would abhor, I would deteſt and reform every ſin: And can you ſtrive more to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, than to ſeem to be religious, and do you endeavour to exceed the beſt opinion that ever any had of you? and do you love a faithfull, ſoul ſearching Miniſtry? that is a great ſign of ſincerity, when a man can ſay, let the word pierce me, let it ſmite me, let it wound and cut me, ſo it may cure me, let it wound my ſin, ſo it may ſave my ſoul: do you love that Miniſtry, that comes moſt to the quick, and that diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers moſt of your ſecret corruptions to you? If it be thus with you, it is a ſign you are Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and therefore a people, whom he will never caſt off: the Lord will be your God now, and at death, and after death, and to all eternity.</p>
            <p>But now on the contrary (and pray mark it) if you be ſuch as chooſe the World for your Portion, rather than God for your Portion, if the world have the cream of your affections, if it have the higheſt ſeat and room in your hearts, if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150135:21"/>you be ſuch as ſeek the world, more than God, earth more than heaven (for as I have ſometimes told you he that ſeeks earth, more than heaven, may well get earth, but he ſhall never get heaven) if you ſerve the world more than God, and if you be ſuch who truſt in men more than you truſt in God; if you be as the Apoſtle ſpeaks,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Tim. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>lovers of pleaſures more than lovers of God;</hi> in a word, if you be hypocrites having onely a form of godlyneſs without the power of it; if you be Apoſtates, falling from your principles, and from your own profeſſion, and draw back (O!<note place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> ſaith God, <hi>That man that draws back, my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</hi>) If you be ſuch as are impenitent, and ſtubborn, and unreformed under all correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and under all inſtructions, that <hi>The lead is conſumed, and the bellowes burnt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 6.29.</note> and all to no purpoſe; if all means uſed for your reformation are ineffectuall, that no good hath been wrought upon you, after ſo many Sermons, after ſo many warnings, after ſo many correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150135:21"/>after ſo many checks of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, after ſo many knockings at the doors of your hearts by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God; if it be thus with you, then you may fear you are in the number of thoſe that God will caſt off, and caſtaway, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.30. <hi>Reprobate ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall men call them, becauſe the Lord hath rejected them;</hi> The Lord hath caſt them off for ever: O! that the Lord would make ſome of you, your own judges, by theſe ſeaven interrogatories, I have now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to you; by theſe and the like diſcoveries you may know whether you are in the number of thoſe this Doctrine here ſpeaks of, that God will never caſt off; this is the firſt exhortation, If you would have the comfort of this Doctrine make this ſure to your ſelves, that you are Gods <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My ſecond exhortation is this, If God will never caſt off his people, his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as it is here in the Text, he is the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> is in captivity. Then I beſeech you, let it be a powerfull perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to every one of us, that ſeeing
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150135:22"/>God is unwilling to caſt us off, that we would be unwilling to caſt God off; will not God caſt off his people, then let us who are his people, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve never to caſt off him: how ſweet and ſavoury,<note place="margin">Joſh. 3.8.</note> is that councel of <hi>Joſhua</hi> to the Iſraelites, <hi>but cleave unto the Lord your God as ye have done unto this day.</hi> O! cleave to this God: we live in times of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy, wherein ſome fall from their Principles, others fall from their profeſſion, and others fall from the practiſe of a Godly life. O! the wofull Apoſtacy, defection, and backſliding of theſe times of ours! that which <hi>Eliphaz</hi> falſely charged upon <hi>Job,</hi> may be truly charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many Profeſſors in theſe days, <hi>thou caſteſt off fear,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>and reſtraineſt prayer before God.</hi> There are many in theſe dayes that caſt off the fear of God, and walk in wayes of liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm, and looſneſs, and that caſt off duty towards God, and duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Superiours; and there are ſome that caſt off love to Chriſt, his truth and ſervants, and that caſt off his Ordinances too. O! the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150135:22"/>Lord open their eyes, that they may ſee what a Wilderneſs they have brought their poor ſouls into, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without Gods great mercy, at the very gates of death and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ruine; but I beſeech you my brethren, be not you of this number, but as God ſpeaks in the like caſe,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.15.</note> 
               <hi>though Iſrael play the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, yet let not Judah offend,</hi> ſo may I ſay, though many Apoſtate and backſlide in theſe daies, yet be not you in the number of them, be not you Apoſtates and backſliders. I beſeech you tell me what hath God done, that you ſhould caſt him off? come and teſtifie againſt him this day wherein hath he done you hurt? what iniquity have you found in God, that you are weary of him? as our Saviour faith, John 10.32. <hi>many good works, have I ſhewed you, from my Father, for which of thoſe works do you ſtone mee?</hi> So may I ſay to you, many mercies hath God beſtowed upon you, mercy upon mercy, mercies of his right hand, and mercies of his left hand, mercies poſitive, and mercies pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150135:23"/>mercies in hand, and mercies in hope, now for which of all theſe mercies have you caſt him off? O hearken to that counſell 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. <hi>The Lord is with you while ye be with him, and if ye ſeek him he will be found of you, but if ye forſake him he will forſake you;</hi> if you caſt him off here, he will caſt you off at that great day, when you would give all the world for one ſmile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his face.</p>
            <p>The laſt Uſe of this Doctrine is this,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>4</label> Doth not God really caſt off his people when be doth it ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? is he <hi>Iſraels</hi> God when <hi>Iſrael</hi> is in captivity? this then is matter of unſpeakable comfort to all Gods people, to all true <hi>Nathanaels</hi> whoſe hearts are ſincere and upright; in the midſt of all their ſtreights, and doubts, and fears, in the midſt of all their troubles, and tryals, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and diſtreſſes whatſoever: what though God caſt thee upon thy bed of ſickneſs, where thou maiſt meet with ſtrong pains, yet he will not caſt thee off: and what though God caſt thee into priſon, yet he will not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150135:23"/>caſt thee off: &amp; what though God caſt thee into captivity, and into a Land of ſtrangers and bondage, yet he will not caſt thee off: Nay what though God caſt thee into ſuch a condition, that thou art out of the reach of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane help, as in the caſe of diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and deſertion; in the caſe of diſtraction, none can reſtore the uſe of reaſon but he that gave us reaſon; and in the caſe of deſertion, none can take off wrath from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience but he that ſet it on. What though God caſt thee into ſuch a condition, that thou walkeſt in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſeeſt no light, yet God will not caſt thee off: Nay what though God ſhould let looſe Sathan upon thee for a while to buffet thee, as you know S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> had an Angel of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than to buffet him; ſo Sathan may be let looſe upon thee to buffet thee, to tempt thee with the batteries of hell, why yet he will not caſt thee off, nay God will ſo order it, that although his temptation may wound thy ſoul, yet it ſhall not hurt thy ſoul; <hi>Thou haſt thruſt ſore at me that I might fall</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150135:24"/>of <hi>Saul</hi>) Pſal. 18.13. <hi>but the Lord helped me:</hi> ſo Sathan thruſts ſore at us, O many a bitter ſtroak, and many a poiſoned arrow, and many a fiery dart Sathan ſeeks to wound us with at one time or other; I but God is our help, God will not caſt us off for all that: True indeed <hi>we are troubled on every ſide yet not diſtreſſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>we are perplexed but not in despair:</hi> It is an elegant expreſſion in the Greek tongue,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>perplexed but not in deſpair, perſecuted but not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, caſt down but not deſtroyed:</hi> Caſt down, I but not caſt off: we may be caſt into adverſity, and be caſt off by men, and yet not be caſt off by God for all that: O what a conſolation may this be to every one of Gods children! That is an excellent Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.10. <hi>For the mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be removed, but my kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the Covenaxt of my peace be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, ſaith the Lord that hath mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy on thee.</hi> O comfort your ſelves with that Text of Scripture: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Apoſtle ſaith triumphing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150135:24"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35, to the end; <hi>Who ſhall ſeparate us from the love of Chriſt? ſhall tribulation, or diſtreſs, or perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, or famine, or nakedneſs, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, or ſword? nay,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in all theſe things we are more than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querers.</hi> We conquer when kil'd, kil'd and not deſtroyed; death may make a ſeparation between body and ſoul, but it can never make a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration between the ſoul and Chriſt; <hi>Neither things preſent, nor things to come,</hi> nor bonds, nor impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor ſickneſs, nor baniſhment nor fiery Furnace, nor Lionsden, nor Principalities, nor powers, nor life, nor death, nor Devils, nor any thing ſhall ever make a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and his people, he will never caſt them off in any of theſe conditions: O that we could but ſuck the ſweetneſs of this conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and lay it up as a Cordiall for a fainting day. And thus I have done with the firſt Point of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, gathered from the firſt branch of the Text, the Author of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable meſſage, it is <hi>the Lord, the God of Iſrael,</hi> he is <hi>Iſraels</hi> God when
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150135:25"/>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> is carried captive; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though God may caſt off his people ſeemingly, yet he doth not caſt them off when he ſeems to caſt them off.</p>
            <p>It remains I ſhould come to the ſecond branch of the Text, and that is the meſſage it ſelf, <hi>I will own them and acknowledge them</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>like theſe good figgs.</hi> But of that I ſhall ſpeak ſomething by Gods aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the further proſecution of the Text.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150135:25"/>
            <head>SERMON II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jeremiah Chap. 24. Verſe 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, the God of Iſrael, Like theſe good Figs, ſo will I acknowledge them that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away captive of Judah, whom I have ſent out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou know what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance I made into this Text; two parts I ſhewed are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in it, The Author of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Meſſage, and the Meſſage</p>
            <p>ſelf: The Author of the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Meſſage is <hi>the Lord,</hi> deſcribed here by his relation to his people, <hi>the God of Iſrael,</hi> and this firſt branch I have diſpatched.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150135:26"/>I come now to the ſecond branch of the Text, and that is the Meſſage it ſelf: Wherein we have firſt the explication of a Type, and then the application of it.</p>
            <p>The explication of a Type in theſe words, <hi>Like theſe good Figs:</hi> where the Lord informs the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> what is the meaning of the Viſion of the two baskets of Figs, the one of good Figs, the other of bad Figs; <hi>Like theſe good Figs</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>ſo are all thoſe good or godly perſons whom I have ſent away captive into Babylon;</hi> ſo that God here compares the ſmall number of godly ones that were yet carried captive to <hi>Babylon,</hi> to Figs; and he compares them to good Figs.</p>
            <p>But here it may be demanded firſt, Why are theſe godly perſons compared to Figs?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, For theſe three Reaſons briefly:
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, Becauſe all the goodneſs they had in them was of Gods own planning, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.21. <hi>The branch of my planting, the work of my hands that I may be glorified.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:150135:26"/>Secondly, They are compared to Figs, becauſe as Figs you know ever grow more and more till they come to a ripeneſs and maturity, that they may be fit for the Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that planted them, ſo did theſe godly perſons grow more and more in grace, till they came to ſome ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and maturity, that they might be fit for the ſervice of that God who had beſtowed this grace upon them, fit to glorifie him here, and fit to be glorified of him hereafter.</item>
                  <item>And then thirdly, As Figs when they are ripe they are very pleaſant and delightfull, they were much eſteemed and deſired among the <hi>Jews,</hi> as appears by <hi>Hoſea</hi> 9.10. <hi>I ſaw your fathers</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>as the firſt ripe in the Fig tree:</hi> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe theſe godly perſons that had the Image of God ſtampt upon them, and were now trees of righte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ouſneſs, that brought forth fruit unto God, they were very delightfull unto God, God was well pleaſed with them; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.11. <hi>The Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pleaſure in them that fear him, in thoſe that hope in his mercy.</hi> (And
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150135:27"/>by the way you may obſerve there, a very ſweet conjunction between fearing God and putting our truſt in his mercy; we muſt ſo fear the Lord, that we ſtill put our truſt in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, leſt we ſhould deſpair; and ſo put our truſt in his mercy, that we fear him, leſt we ſhould preſume:) but that I quote the Scripture for is this the Lord delights in them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fear him, and it is very much that God ſhould take delight in ſuch poor deſpicable creatures as we are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> and we have a very ſtrange expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.17. <hi>I know alſo my God that thou takest pleaſure in uprightneſs:</hi> a wonderfull condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, that the great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth ſhould take pleaſure in any ſervice that ſuch poor worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs worms as we are can perform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> that the Lord ſhould take pleaſur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in us, or in any thing that is in us but we muſt know, that uprightneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is the work of Gods own Spirit i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our hearts, and therefore God fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> beſtowes the graces of his Spirit up on his ſervants, which are call'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the fruits of his Spirit, and then h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150135:27"/>delights in his own fruits, according to that of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.31.</note> 
                     <hi>The Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth in his own works;</hi> that is, in the works of his own Spirit that he hath wrought. And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath a ſweet Meditation upon it; <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do not thou look upon my own works, but look upon thy own works in my heart; for if thou lookeſt upon my works I ſhall be curſed, but if thou lookeſt upon thy own works I ſhall be crowned.</hi> God takes delight in his own works; he crowns his <hi>own</hi> gifts not our merits in us. Thus you ſee why they are called Figs.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, How theſe could be called <hi>good Figs,</hi> when our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour ſaith expreſly, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.17. <hi>There is none good but One, that is God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer, It is true there is none good but onely God, that is, there is none good ſo as God is good, none good in that manner of goodneſs, none good in that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of goodneſs that God is.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God alone is originally good, men are good only by parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150135:28"/>as they partake of the goodneſs of God, but God hath his goodneſs from none, he is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of his own goodneſs, all the goodneſs that is in us, is a deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive goodneſs, it is but a drop of that ocean of goodneſs that is in God: look as the beams of the Sun they proceed from the Sun, but the Sun is the fountain of its own light; ſo all the goodneſs that is in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it proceeds from God, but God (I ſay) is the fountain of his own goodneſs, therefore none is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally good but God, that is the meaning of our Saviour when he faith, <hi>There is none good but One, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly, None is eſſentially good but God, the goodneſs of God it is his very nature, it is his very eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; for that is a true rule amongſt Divines,<note place="margin">Quicquid in Deo, Deus eſt.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever is in God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God himſelf:</hi> the goodneſs of God is God himſelf, and ſo the mercy of God is God himſelf, and the love of God is God himſelf; if there be any goodneſs in the ſons of men, it is but a quality a property that is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150135:28"/>from the eſſence; for a man may be a man and yet not a good man, but God cannot be God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he be good; God can as ſoon ceaſe to be God, as ceaſe to be good, goodneſs being eſſentially in him.</p>
            <p>And then thirdly, There is none abſolutely and perfectly good but onely God, God is every way good, and he is ſo perfectly good that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be added to him, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be detracted from him: now it cannot be ſaid of any man living upon the earth, that he is perfectly good, for alas our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is mixt with a great deal of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſs and infirmity, our gold is mingled with a great deal of droſs, but God is abſolutely good.</p>
            <p>And fourthly, God is unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably good, <hi>there is in him no vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs nor ſhadow of turning,</hi> Jam. 1.17. but now it is not ſo with us, our goodneſs for the moſt part is very fickle and unconſtant.</p>
            <p>And then laſtly, God cals theſe godly perſons that were ſent into captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>good Figs,</hi> not ſo much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to their inherent ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150135:29"/>as in reſpect of his own gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious acceptation, he accepted them in Jeſus Chriſt the Saviour of the world, whoſe blood was ſhed from the foundation of the world, and ſo beholding them in Chriſt, he lookt upon them as good, as righteous, as godly perſons. Now obſerve (and it is worth our obſervation) that at this time when the land of <hi>Judah</hi> was filled with abominations from one end thereof unto the other, at this time when the iniquity of the land of <hi>Judah</hi> was boyled up to that height that it ſpued out the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the land, at this time when the multitude of ſinners provoked the Lord ſo to anger, that he ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon them the line of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and the plummet of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> that is, gave the ſame Cup into their bands to drink that he did to the ten Tribes; at this time when God threatned to wipe <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> as a man wipes a diſh when he turns it upſide down, as we have it 2 <hi>King,</hi> 21.13. yet obſerve there were ſome good even at this time, here was a basket of good Figs, that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150135:29"/>yet notwithſtanding were carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed captive into <hi>Babylon.</hi> The Doctrine then that I would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you from hence is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That in the worst of times and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the worſt of men,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>God will ſtill have a remnant of thoſe that are good, and that ſhall retain their goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Noahs</hi> time when there was ſuch a deluge of ſin that it brought a deluge of water to drown the world, when all fleſh had corrupted their wayes upon earth, and God repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that he had made man, and it grieved him at his very heart, yet it is ſaid, that <hi>Noah</hi> was upright in that generation;<note place="margin">Gen. 6.10.</note> and it was a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er honour to him to be upright in that generation, than to have been upright in a godly generation: <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jah</hi> lived in as corrupt an age I think as ever any man lived in, for he complains he had no man to ſtand by him; O ſaies he, <hi>the children of Iſrael have forſaken thy Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 King 19.10.</note> 
               <hi>thrown down thine Altars, and ſlain thy Prophets with the ſword, and I even I only am left.</hi> There was not ſo much as a face of Religion ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150135:30"/>and he thought there had not been one godly man left in all the land of <hi>Iſrael</hi> beſides himſelf, and yet at that very time God had ſome that were good,<note place="margin">v. 18.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſeven thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi> (ſaies God) <hi>that have not bowed their knees to Baal.</hi> In the declining times of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> God yet <hi>Judah</hi> that was faithfull to him. Hoſea 11.12. <hi>Ephrain compaſſeth me about with lies, and the houſe of Iſrael with deceit, but Judah yet ruleth with God, and is faithfull with the Saints.</hi> In the declining times of <hi>Judah,</hi> when there was a very great defection and apoſtacy; as you may read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>In hearing you ſhall hear and not underſtand, and in ſeeing you ſhall ſee but not perceive:</hi> when their hearts were hardened to their deſtruction, yet notwithſtanding God had <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Baruch,</hi> and a basket of good Figs, that is, thoſe that were very good, even in the worſt times of <hi>Judah,</hi> in the times of their captivity. In the Prophet <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time there was a very ſinfull and ſhamefull apoſtacy, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.21, 22, 23. ſaies the Lord (complaining
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150135:30"/>of them) <hi>How is the faithfull City</hi> (ſpeaking of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) <hi>become an harlot? it was full of judgment, righteouſneſs lodged in it, but now murtherers: thy ſilver is become droſs, thy wine mixt with water, thy Princes are rebellious, and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of thieves, every one loveth gifts, and followeth after rewards; they judge not the fatherleſs, neither doth the cauſe of the widow come unto them.</hi> But yet even in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time there was a remnant like a Teyl tree, and as an Oak whoſe ſubſtance is in them when they have caſt their leaves;<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.13.</note> there ſhall be a little rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant like an Oak that hath the ſap in it; ſo ſaies God, <hi>the holy ſeed ſhall be the ſtability of it.</hi> The Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> was for the moſt part hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and corrupt,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.3, 4.</note> they had <hi>a name to live when they were dead:</hi> (a juſt Picture of our Times:) yet ſaies God, <hi>thou haſt a few Names even in Sardis which have not defiled their garments, and they ſhall walk with me in white, for they are worthy.</hi> In the times of <hi>Arius</hi> that deſparate he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick that denied the Divinity of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150135:31"/>Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that the whole world groaned as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Jerom</hi> obſerves,<note place="margin">Ingemuit orbis ſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianum.</note> that it was turned Arian, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there was an <hi>Athanaſius</hi> that did help to bear up the truth with courage and confidence againſt all oppoſition: and you know in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, when Popery was here ſet up by a Law, yet there were then many faithfull ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt that ſealed the truth with their blood, and were more willing to lay down their lives for Chriſt, than many now adayes are to part with a little of their eſtates for Chriſt and for the Goſpell; ſo that you ſee, in the worſt of times, and amongſt the worſt of men, the Lord will have ſome that are good, and that retain their goodneſs.</p>
            <p>And if you would know the Reaſons of it, they are theſe;</p>
            <p>Firſt,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Becauſe the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt is an everlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>of his Kingdome there ſhall be no end,</hi> Luk. 1.33. Jeſus Chriſt will have a Church here upon earth mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre the might and malice, the rage and fury, the plots and projects,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150135:31"/>the craft and ſubtiltie of Sathan and all his inſtruments: All the enemies of the Church, may as well think to turn the earth off its hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or pluck the Stars out of the Firmament, or blow out the Sun with a pair of Bellows, or ſhake the pillars of Heaven, as to root out the number of the godly from off the face of the earth, <hi>The gates of Hell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall not prevail againſt the Church.</hi> It is true indeed the Church of Chriſt is not tied to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular place, nor to a ſtinted num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but yet like the ſea, though it loſe in one place, it gains ſtill in another place, and the Church of Chriſt being his ſpouſe, he will never loſe his ſpouſe, he will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes have ſome even in the worſt of times, and in the worſt of places, that ſhall own him and his truth; therefore (you know) he had a Church in <hi>Neroes</hi> Houſe, though <hi>Nero</hi> was one of the bloodieſt Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that ever lived amongſt men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.22. <hi>All the Saints ſalute you, chiefly they that are of Caeſars houſhold:</hi> And he had ſome that did bear up
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150135:32"/>his Name when <hi>Antipas</hi> his faithfull Martyr was ſlain, and where the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil had his Synagogue, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.13. That's one Reaſon.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19.</note> The Foundation of God ſtands ſure, and therefore it is not poſſible that the Elect ſhould be totally ſeduced: our Saviour ſaies indeed there ſhall be ſuch cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſeducers and impoſtors,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note> that if it were poſſible they ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the very Elect; I but that is impoſſible, Gods Elect it is true may ſometimes be hurried into ways of errour and ſin by a Croud, but then their hearts will ſtill be God-ward, juſt as the Needle of the Seamans Compaſs may jog this way, and that way, but the bent of the Needle will ſtill be North-ward; ſo their hearts will be God-ward, and they will recover themſelves, the Spirit is in them like a ſpringing water,<note place="margin">Joh. 4.14.</note> that ſprings up to eternal life, it is an immortal ſeed ſo that they cannot ſin unto death,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 3.9.</note> and the fear of God is the aw-back of the ſoul, it is ſuch an awe upon their ſpirits, that they ſhall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150135:32"/>never totally and finally depart from God. Jer. 32.40. <hi>I will put my fear in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thirdly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> The interceſſion of Jeſus Chriſt is very prevalent for all his Elect,<note place="margin">Luke 22.32.</note> 
               <hi>I have prayed for thee</hi> (faies Chriſt to <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>that thy faith fail not,</hi> and this prayer he made not for <hi>Peter</hi> onely, but for all that ſhall believe in his Name to the end of the world, as appears by John 17.20. <hi>Neither pray I for theſe alone, but for them alſo which ſhall believe on me through their word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then fourthly and laſtly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> God will alwaies have a remnant of good ones of Godly Perſons, that ſhall retain their goodneſs even for this very end, to convince gainſayers, to ſtop the mouthes of wicked &amp; ungodly men that are ever blattering againſt the truth; he will have ſome that ſhall bear witneſs againſt them, that they ſhall not plead ignorance, of that truth they ſo much ſcorn and contemn, and of the ways of holineſs, which they ſo
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150135:33"/>much abhor: as God would have the Goſpel preached, if not for converſion, yet for conviction, to be a teſtimony againſt them that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it not. Mat. 24.14, ſaies Chriſt, <hi>this Goſpel of the Kingdom, ſhall be preached in all the world for a witneſs unto all Nations;</hi> ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God will have ſome faithfull ones to be his <hi>Martyrs,</hi> to lift up his name, and to bear witneſs ſtill unto his truth, againſt them that oppoſe it, and to riſe up in judgement againſt thoſe that are the deſperate and implacable enemies of it,<note place="margin">Heb. 11.7.</note> as it is ſaid of <hi>Noah,</hi> by building the Ark he condemned the world, that is his righteouſneſs condemned their unrighteouſneſs, his faithfulneſs condemned their infidelity, his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity condemned their hypocriſie, and his ſteadfaſtneſs condemned their apoſtacy, ſo God (I ſay) will ſtill have ſome to bear witneſs, and to judge the wicked of the world, when he ſhall have a little number that will own him, when others do diſown him, and deſpiſe him.</p>
            <p>Now for the uſe of this Point,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150135:33"/>If it be ſo that God will ſtill have ſome in bad times that are good and retain their goodneſs,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> then I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you tell me, are you good in bad times, are you the better, the the worſs the times are? my brethren I need not tell you that we live in ſad and ſinfull times, for certainly iniquity, atheiſme and hereſie are boyled up to a greater heighth in theſe three or four years laſt paſt, than they were in forty years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: now doubtleſs in ſuch diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing and trying times as theſe are, you will either be very good or elſe very bad; you will be like one of theſe two baskets of Figs, the good Figs were very good, and the bad were very bad; tell me then whether you be good Figs, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be bad Figs?<note place="margin">Jer. 24.2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now to help you in this ſcrutiny, there are but theſe three queſtions I would propound to you, and I wiſh you would propound them to your own ſouls: Firſt, Are you impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially good? Secondly, Are you ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely good? Thirdly, Are you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly good? Let me ſpeak to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150135:34"/>one of theſe heads a little.</p>
            <p>Firſt tell me, Are you impartially good? have you reſpect to all the Commandments of God? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed when I have reſpect to all thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> Do you reſpect every command without partiality and without hypocriſie? as the Apoſtle hath it 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.25. Do you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide things honeſt in the ſight of God, and in the ſight of men? in the fight of God in the duties of the firſt Table, and in the ſight of men in the duties of the ſecond Table? do you ſtudy to be righteous in reference to the ſecond Table, as well as to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious in reference to the firſt Table? This is to be truly good, if you be thus impartially good with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out halfing it in the waies of Gods Commandements. I beſeech you conſider and remember this, he that makes no conſcience of the Duties of the ſecond Table, God abhors all the Duties that he performs in reference to the firſt Table; as now if you be unjuſt in your trading, if you be injurious in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150135:34"/>your dealing, if you rob the poor, becauſe he is poor, and oppreſs the needy in the gate; if you ſell the needy for a piece of ſilver, and the poor for a pair of ſhooes, if you take advantage of the poors ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, if you withhold from him that which is his right, if you detain the hire of the labourer, and of him that takes pains for you, as the Apoſtle S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi> ſaies, <hi>Behold the hire of the labourers which have reaped down your Corn, which is detained of you by frand cryeth, and the cries of them which have reaped, are entred into the ears of the Lord of Sabbath,</hi> James 5.4. (whereby the way you may obſerve, that if the detaining the labourers wages, that did reap down their Corn, was ſuch a crying ſin, what is it think you then to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their right that take pains in the Lords vineyard, and labour in the Lords harveſt? I pray God it be not laid to the charge of many in this City) if you be unrighteous I ſay in detaining that which is due to the labourer, if you be unmercifull, if you be uncharitable, in your cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150135:35"/>of others, know thus much, that there is no goodneſs at all in you; though you make never ſo much ſhew of Religion: if you do not make conſcience of duties in the ſhop, God regards not all the duties you perform in the Church and on the Lords dayes; if you do not make conſcience of the ninth command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt bear no falſe witneſs againſt thy neighbour,</hi> thou ſhalt not flander thy neighbour, thou ſhalt not reproach thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, God regards not your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aation of the fourth Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for keeping of the Lords day: and this appears by what S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi> ſaies, <hi>If any man among you ſeem to be religious and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, that mans religion is vain,</hi> James 1.26. And indeed it is a thing very obſervable, that the Spirit of God makes the duties of the ſecond Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be a touch-ſtone to try the truth of our duties to the firſt Table: pray remember it, I will give you but two inſtances for it. Firſt, that in <hi>James</hi> 1.27. <hi>Pure religion and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150135:35"/>before God and the Father is this, to viſit the Fatherleſs, and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows in their affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the world:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Would you know whether you be truly religious or no, then ſee whether you be truly righteous, yea or no. And the other Scripture is 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.20. <hi>If a man ſay he loves God, and hateth his brother, he is a lyar, for he that loveth not his brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God, whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, Would you know whether you love God yea or no, (which is the duty of the firſt Table) then ſee whether you love your brother yea or no, which is the duty of the ſecond Table. Some men are all for holineſs but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for righteouſneſs; ſome on the contrary are all for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but nothing for holineſs: But I beſeech you my brethren remember this, God hates an unrighteous ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man as much as he hates an unho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteous man: Righteouſneſs and holineſs the duties of the two Tables muſt go both together. <hi>He
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150135:36"/>hath delivered us out of the hands of our enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 1.74, 75.</note> 
               <hi>that we might ſerve him without fear in holineſs and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs before him all the dayes of our life.</hi> And therefore know thus much, that although thou beeſt a man of never ſo excellent parts, and canſt talk never ſo much of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Scripture, and haſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and admirable gifts in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo that thou canſt pray like an Angel; yet if thou doſt not make conſcience of the duties of the ſecond Table, God abhors all thy parts and gifts, and holy language, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion whatſoever. This is the firſt queſtion, Are you righteous as well as religious, and religious as well as righteous? Do you walk with an even foot towards the duties of both Tables?</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Let me ask you this queſtion, Are you ſincerely good? Are you inwardly good? There are many that are ſeemingly good, but few that are really good; many that are outwardly good, but few that are inwardly good. You know what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:150135:36"/>2.28, 29. <hi>He is not a Jew which is one outwardly, neither is that Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion which is outward in the fleſh, but he is a Jew which is one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and Circumciſion is that of the heart, whoſe praiſe is not of men but of God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 16.7.</note> God ſees not as man ſees; man looks at the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, but God looks to the heart:<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.6.</note> 
               <hi>Thou loveſt truth in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts.</hi> Give me an inward Chriſtian; give me a Chriſtian that is ever communing with his own heart, that is ever turning his eyes inwards and his heart outwards to God, this is a good Chriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. Hypocrites can perform out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward holy duties, and many times outſtrip thoſe that are ſincere, and yet in the mean time they are but painted ſepulchres, fair without, but within full of corruption; they are but as a dunghill covered over with ſnow, that appears very white without, but within there is nothing but filthineſs; they are but as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> fair without and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten within. There are many that are ſeemingly Saints, outwardly
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150135:37"/>Saints, but inwardly they are no better than Devils. But now tell me, Are you the ſame within that you are without? Are your ſpirits not only free from guilt, but free from guile:<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.2</note> 
               <hi>O bleſſed is the man in whoſe ſpirit there is no guile.</hi> Are you good towards the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which was the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Abijah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 1 King. 14.13. <hi>There was found ſome good thing in him toward the Lord God of Iſrael.</hi> Indeed unſound and rotten-hearted Chriſtians may be good towards men, I but they are not good towards the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But if you be inwardly good, if you be ſincerely good, then are you good indeed. <hi>Luther</hi> relates a Story of a man that had led a very righteous, innocent, and unblamea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life; but when he came upon his ſick bed, he felt his heart full of doubts, and fears, and diſquietments, and was much troubled about his ſpiritual eſtate; ſome of his friends came to him, and ſaid to him, O Sir why are you troubled about your ſpiritual eſtate, you have lived a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150135:37"/>moſt righteous, a moſt innocent, and unblameable life. I (ſaies he) it is true, I have led ſuch a life in your eyes, but the eye of man, and the eye of God, doe exceedingly differ. The judgement of man is one thing, (ſaies he) but the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God is another thing. And therefore notwithſtanding all my innocent life, which you ſo much applaud, I am afraid to die. I would apply it thus: If the godly, the righteous, thoſe that are ſincere, are ſo much troubled at the dregs of Guile, and Hppocriſie, that are in their own hearts, O! what cauſe then have they to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that have no ſincerity at all in them. And when that great day comes, wherein the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be made manifeſt; wherein God will diſcloſe the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the heart, and all thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret rottenneſſes, and uncleaneſſes, that are in mens ſpirits, when that day ſhall come,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.5.</note> which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, that will be a day of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, of all that inward filthineſs, that is now diſguiſed, and cloakt,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150135:38"/>under a fair pretence of holineſs, and the like, O! where then will ſuch ungodly ones, where will ſuch rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hearted ſinners be able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear? Let this therefore be the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond queſtion, Are you ſincerely good, or are you rotten at heart yea or no?</p>
            <p>And then thirdly, Anſwer to this queſtion (and then I will tell you whether you are good, or no.) Are you conſtantly good? are you ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly good? God complains of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> Hoſea 6.4. <hi>O Ephraim, what ſhall I doe unto thee? O Judah, what ſhall I doe unto thee?</hi> (as if he ſhould ſay, I know not what courſe to take with you) <hi>for your goodneſs is as a morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away,</hi> that is, their goodneſs was of no continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at all; many ſuch there are in theſe dayes, they are not conſtant in that which is good, they begin in the ſpirit, but end in the fleſh, they are good for a while, but afterwards they ſhamefully fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, either from the truth, or from the love, or from the Obedience of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150135:38"/>the Goſpell; Juſt like your young Scholars, that begin newly to write, it may be they write two or three let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters very handſomely, but by and by they blur all their copy. O! take heed you be not ſuch; but if you be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, unmoveable, abounding in the work of the Lord; if you hold out to the end; if you retain your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity in the worſt of times; if you be faithfull to God, his cauſe and truth; if you be eſtabliſhed in the truth; and doe not ſtart aſide, and are not led away with the error of the wicked, to fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs; if you be ſtedfaſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, than are you good Chriſtians. Anſwer but theſe three queſtions, and then I can tell whether you are good or no. This is the firſt Uſe, I ſhould have call'd it a Uſe of examination; you ſhould call your ſelves to an account, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be good Figs, or bad Figs: Alas this is a time wherein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grow worſe and worſe;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 2 Tim. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Evill men and ſeducers wax worſe and worſe,</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle) every day: juſt like a round ſtone upon the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150135:39"/>top of a hill, when once it begins to tumble, it tumbles, and tumbles, and tumbles till it comes to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome. O! this is the caſe of many at this day, they run from errour to errour, from ſin to ſin, and from one wickedneſs to another, till they plunge themſelves irrecoverably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pit of deſtruction; but ſee whether you grow better and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and retain your own goodneſs, whether you be impartially good, ſincerely good, and conſtantly good, yea or no?</p>
            <p>My ſecond Uſe, is for exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Let me beſeech, and exhort you this day in the Name of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, (whoſepoor Meſſenger I am) That every one of you would ſtrive to be good in bad Times; that you would endeavour to be like <hi>Lot</hi> in <hi>Sodom,</hi> and to be like Lights in the world, in the mideſt of a Crooked,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.16.</note> and Preverſe Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; holding forth the word of life, and holding faſt the word of truth: There is a holding forth the word of truth, that is by an undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted profeſſion, and a holding faſt the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150135:39"/>word of truth, that is by an undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted reſolution, that you would be like to Fiſhes, that retain their freſhneſs in the ſalt-water. O! that I could perſwade you to doe as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, (not onely to ſay ſo but do ſo) <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.33. <hi>Though all men ſhall be offended becauſe of thee yet will I never be offended.</hi> How many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives might I uſe to preſs you to this?</p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider by doing this, you ſhall be like unto your God, for it is ſaid of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.68. <hi>Thou art good, and doeſt good.</hi> You all hope to be like unto God in glory, labour then to be like unto God in grace; It is ſaid of our bleſſed Saviour,<note place="margin">Act. 10.38.</note> 
               <hi>That he went about doing good, and healing thoſe that were oppreſſed of the devil.</hi> O! that we could labour to be good, and to be doing good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually. But ſome may ſay, how hard a matter is it to be good in bad Times? Alas it is an extream hard matter for a man to retain his integrity then, and to ſwim againſt the ſtream, when there are ſo many ſnares, and ſo many temptations. I anſwer (and I beſeech you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150135:40"/>it) the beſt Chriſtians are ſtill bred up in the worſt times; like as the ſoundeſt ſheep are bred up in the ſhorteſt commons. It is very obſervable, that the Church and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, have ever loſt ground in times of Proſperity, and have ever gained ground in times of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had endowed the Church with large revenews,<note place="margin">Religio pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> it was ſaid, <hi>Religion like a kind mother hath brought forth plenty, but plenty like an unkind daughter hath devoured her mother.</hi> And it is obſerved, that in <hi>Diacleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> time; which was the Tenth, and laſt perſecution; the more Religion was oppoſed, the more a thouſand times it proſpered, inſomuch that that bloody Emperour, when he ſaw that the more he ſtrove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, the leſſe he prevailed, and the more he thought to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Religion, the more it thrived, he went in a pet, and ſaid down his Empire, and betook himſelf to a ſolitary life, he ſaw there was no good to be done that way: And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Hilary</hi> that lived in the times of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150135:40"/>that perſecutor, did profeſſe, that he was more afraid of Toleration, than of perſecution; and he gives this reaſon, For (ſaies he) <hi>the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of Religion will make men Appoſtates, but the perſecution of Religion uſually makes men Martyrs.</hi> So that the Church gains by Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and by troubles, and God looks you ſhould be the beſt Chriſtians in the worſt times; and it will be a great token of your ſincerity, if you can hold your own at that time, when others are warping and declining.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, take another motive, and 'tis this, conſider if you be good amongſt thoſe that are bad, good in bad, Times, this is that which will bring moſt honour to God, whoſe honour ſhould be dearer to us than our own lives: It is obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able that Chriſt teacheth us to pray for Gods glory before our own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; <hi>Hollowed be thy name,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>thy Kingdome come,</hi> The honour of God was ſo wonderfully dear to him: Now this brings moſt honour to God, when you as his faithfull ſervants can own his truth, when
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150135:41"/>moſt diſown it. As that Souldier doth moſt honour his Captain, who ſtands his ground, when all his fellow Souldiers turn their backs; ſo this is that which will honour God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if you ſtick to him when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers fall off, and fall away.</p>
            <p>Nay thirdly Conſider, this is that which will bring moſt honour to your ſelves, and your profeſſion; for look, as for a man to be evill in the beſt of times; to be evill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are good; this is the height of impiety: So on the contrary, for a man to be good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that are evill, this is the height of Piety: 'tis a very eaſie matter to be good amongſt thoſe that are good, to be good in good times, when it is a credit, and an honour to profeſſe Religion; hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites you know when they come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe that are godly, they will appear to be godly; <hi>Judas</hi> when he was in the School of Chriſt, carryed himſelf ſo fairly and inoffencively, that all the Diſciples ſuſpected themſelves, rather than <hi>Judas,</hi> and ſaid <hi>Maſter is it I?</hi> But now when a man can
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150135:41"/>own the truth, when others oppoſe it, and deſpiſeit; when a man fears God at that time when others caſt off fear, and ſticks to truth when others are aſhamed of truth: When a man likewiſe keeps his warmth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt frozen Chriſtians, and his Spirituall life amongſt dead and drowſie Chriſtians; and his Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all groweth amongſt decaying, and declining Chriſtians: This is the Honour, this is the Crown of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity.</p>
            <p>And then fourthly, Conſider this, If you be good in the worſt of times, certainly God will take care of you, and the leſs encouragement you have from men, the more encouragement you ſhall have from God; and the leſs you are owned by men, the more you ſhall be owned by God. God had a care of theſe poor Captives, this basket of good Figs, were carryed Captive into the Land of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bylon,</hi> I but God was with them, he ſtood by them (as I ſhould have ſpoken to that point, if time would have given me leave,) and God did own and acknowledge them, ſo God will
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150135:42"/>own, and honour you, and ſtand by you, and ſtrengthen and ſupport you, and cauſe all your afflictions to work for your good; he will but prove you, that he may doe you good in the latter end; this is the ſecond Uſe, a Uſe of exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Thirdly and laſtly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> It may ſerve greatly for the encouragement, and conſolation of the godly in the worſt of times; let the times be never ſo deſparate, you ſee God will have a Number, ſome that will be faithfull to him, that will own him. and his cauſe, that will help, to bear up his truth and Name, that will hold faſt their profeſſion without waver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; 'tis true indeed, the Church of Chriſt may be like a Ship toſſed, but it can never be overturned, it may be toſſed becauſe it is upon the Sea, but it can never be overturned becauſe Jeſus Chriſt is in it. The Church may be drenched in ſorrow, but it cannot be drowned in miſery. Therefore we ſhould bear up our hearts in the very worſt of times; and we ſhould ſtill cleave unto God,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150135:42"/>that he may cleave unto us; let us lift up thoſe hands that hang down, and thoſe feeble knees, there are more with us than againſt us; if one God be with us, it is more than if ten thouſand worlds were againſt us. And know this, we ſhall never have cauſe to repent of our cleaving to God though in the worſt of times. And ſo much ſhall ſuffice to have ſpoken of this ſecond Doctrine, which is drawn from the firſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular of the ſecond branch of the Text, the explication of the Type.</p>
            <p>I had thought to have ſpoken to the other particular; namely the application of it to theſe poor Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; <hi>So will I acknowledge them, I will own them, I will take ſpeciall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of them that are carryed away Captive of Judah.</hi> The Doctrine I ſhould have ſpoken to from hence is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God doth own his people,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>and acknowledge them in the day of their dangers and diſtreſſes.</hi> He owns them by being preſent with them, and he owns them by ſupporting of them, and he owns them by deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150135:43"/>of them, and he owns them becauſe he bears a love to them, no change of condition can change his affections towards them. O! the faithfullneſs of our God; you ſee freinds ſtand aloof off many times in the day of adverſity; but God is a faithfull friend, he is ever neareſt when trouble is near; and when he brings us into the worſt conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he is uſually the beſt God unto us. The <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath a ſweet paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.24. <hi>For he hath not abhorred nor deſpiſed the affliction of the afflicted: neither hath he bid his face from him, but when he cryed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him he heard him.</hi> God doth not deſpiſe the affliction of his people, as the manner of ſome is; in the day of their diſtreſs, then they hide away their faces, and will not own nor know thoſe that are afflicted. It is a great comfort and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that God will own his people when the world will not own them, and that God will be with them, and ſtand by them, and ſtick to them when the world re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects them, caſts them off, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150135:43"/>ſtands at a diſtance from them: <hi>I will acknowledge them ſaith God.</hi> But I ſee the time is too far ſpent, and I will not further intrench, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon your patience or my own ſtrength. So much ſhall ſuffice for this time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:150135:44"/>
            <head>SERMON III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jeremiah Chap. 24. Verſe 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, the God of Iſrael, Like theſe good Figs, ſo-will I acknowledge them that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away captive of Judah, whom I have ſent out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou may remember how far I proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in opening this Text, unto you in two Sermons the the laſt Lords day. I have done with the Explication of the Type, <hi>like theſe good Figs;</hi> being the firſt particular of the ſecond branch of the Text, namely the Meſſage it ſelf.</p>
            <p>I come now unto the Application
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150135:44"/>of this Type of the good Figs, unto theſe poor Captives, and the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it (if you look upon the Text) is wholly comfortable, and the comfort God reacheth out unto them under the Type of theſe good Figs, is three fold.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, He tels them he would <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge</hi> them, whom he had ſent away Captive of <hi>Judah.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, He tels them that it was <hi>he</hi> that had ſent them out of that place, into the Land of the <hi>Calde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And thirdly, He tels them that it was for their Spiritual profit and advantage; it was for their <hi>good.</hi> Every one of theſe will afford, us a point of Doctrine, and I ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance give you them in this, and another Sermon in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon.</item>
            </list>
            <p>We will begin with the Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Meſſage, in the firſt way of comfort, ſaies God, <hi>So will I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge them that are carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Captive of Judah.</hi> So will I acknowledge them; that is I will own them, I will take ſpeciall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150135:45"/>of them; Mine eyes and my heart ſhall be toward them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I have ſent them away Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into <hi>Bahylon;</hi> yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they ſhall know that I am their freind, and I am their father ſtill, and that I have not caſt them off. The point of Doctrine then that I would commend to you from hence is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God doth graciouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>and own his ſervants in the day of their dangers and diſtreſſes.</hi> Pſal. 31.7. <hi>Thou haſt conſidered my trouble, thou haſt known my ſoul in adverſity.</hi> And that is a comfortable Scripture, <hi>Pſ</hi> 22.24. <hi>he hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed, nor abhorred the affliction of the afflicted, neither hath he hid his face from him, but when he cryed unto him he heard him.</hi> God doth not abhor, nor deſpiſe the affliction of his poor afflicted ſervants, he doth not hide away his face from them; he doth no look aſide as if he regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them not in the day of their diſtreſſes. God owned his people <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when they were among the Brickilns; when they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150135:45"/>were making their Pots, when they were poor Bondſlaves, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22. ſaies God there to <hi>Moſes Go to Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh and ſay, Thus ſaith the Lord, Iſrael is my ſon even my firſt born, and therefore let him go.</hi> As if the Lord ſhould ſay, although <hi>Iſrael</hi> be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Pots, yet he is my ſon ſtill, and although he be under Bondage, yet he is my firſt born ſtill. How paſſionately and affectionately doth God ſpeak, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.34. <hi>I have ſeen, I have ſeen the affliction of my people which is in Egypt,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemination of the word ſhewes the earſtneſs of Gods affections, as I may call them, (not that God hath affections, but it is ſpoken after the manner of men becauſe he doth that which men doe, when their affections and bowels yearn toward thoſe that are in miſery) <hi>and his ſoul was grieved for the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the explication of the Point; It may be demanded.</p>
            <p>Firſt, How doth God own and acknowledge his people in the day of their dangers and diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:150135:46"/>And then ſecondly, why doth he own them?</p>
            <p>Firſt, How doth God own them.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, God owns them three waies.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, By being preſent with them.</item>
               <item>Secondly, By ſupporting of them.</item>
               <item>And thirdly, By delivering them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, God owns his people, in the day of their diſtreſſes, by being preſent with them. Pſal. 91.15. <hi>He ſhall call upon me, and I will anſwer him, I will be with him in trouble.</hi> And Iſa. 43.2. <hi>When thou paſſeſts through the waters, I will be with thee, and through the Rivers they ſhall not overflow thee, when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burned, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon thee.</hi> So in Iſa. 63.9. <hi>In all their affliction he was afflicted, and the Angel of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſaved them.</hi> If <hi>Joſeph</hi> be in Priſon, God will be with him there. If <hi>Job</hi> be on the dunghil, God will be with him there. If <hi>Jeremiah</hi> be in the dungeon, God
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150135:46"/>will be with him there. If <hi>Daniel</hi> be in the Lions-den, God will be with him there. Nay when his Children paſs through the valley of the ſhadow of death, when they paſs as it were by the gates of hell, yet notwithſtanding his rod and his ſtaff do then comfort them; as he once ſaid, thy preſence O Lord it can ſweeten <hi>Lawrence</hi> his Grid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iron; the preſence of God, it can turn a Priſon into a Pallace, it can turn a very hell into a heaven; what makes heaven to be heaven but Gods preſence, and what makes hell to be hell but Gods ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? Now for God to be preſent thus with his people, in their trouble, this is one way of his owning them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God doth own his people in their diſtreſſes, by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting them, by upholding them with the right hand of his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that their burthens ſhall not be too heavy for them, but either he will proportion their burthens to their ſhoulders, or their ſhoulders to their burthens, that they ſhall ſtand
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150135:47"/>under them. Iſa. 41.10. <hi>Fear thou not for I am with thee, be not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed for I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, yea I will help thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſs.</hi> And this is that which <hi>David</hi> found in his own experience, Pſal. 94.17, 18, 19. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs the Lord had been my help, my ſoul had almoſt dwel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſilence; when I ſaid my foot ſlippeth, thy mercy O Lord held me up: In the multitude of my thoughts within me, thy comforts refreſh my ſoul.</hi> It is ſtoried of one <hi>Theodorus</hi> whom <hi>Julian</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate cauſed to be rackt ànd torture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and put to extream torments, that in the midſt of his torments there was an Angel (as <hi>Theodoret</hi> tels the ſtory) in the likeneſs of a young man that ſtood by him, and with a linnen cloath did wipe the ſweat from off him, and powred cool water upon his vexed and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured limbs, and by that means did refreſh and comfort him: and our bleſſed Saviour (you know) in that agony when he ſweat drops of blood, had an Angel with him to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150135:47"/>comfort him; God knows how to comfort and ſupport his Children, and to ſtand by them in the greateſt of their diſtreſſes, and ſo he owns them.</p>
            <p>And then thirdly, God owns his Children by delivering them out of all their diſtreſſes, Pſal. 34.19. <hi>Many are the afflictions of the righteous, but the Lord delivereth him out of them all.</hi> And that is a very remarkeable Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture Jeremiah 50.33.34. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of hoſts, the Children of Iſrael, and the Children of Judah were oppreſſed together, and all that took them Captives held them jaſt, they refuſed to let them go, but their redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is ſtrong, the Lord of hoſts is his Name he ſhall thorowly plead their cauſe, that he may give reſt unto the Land, and diſquiet the in habitants of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> God will not alwaies let the rod of the wicked reſt upon the lot of the righteous. And thus you ſee that God owns his people in their diſtreſſes.</p>
            <p>But then why doth he own them? The reaſon is this briefly, becauſe his children are very dear unto him,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150135:48"/>he looks upon them as his <hi>jewelt,</hi> Mal. 3.17. (a text you know I have heretofore opened unto you) he looks upon them as his precious ones, as the dearly beloved of his ſoul, he looks upon them as the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his own eye, and therefore no change of condition in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren can make God change his love and affections towards them, and though God may ſometimes caſt them into the furnace of affliction, it is onely to purge away their droſs, and he loves them when in the fire as well as when they are out of it, and he is with them and ſtands by them all the while. The uſe of this point is,</p>
            <p>Firſt, By way of Inſtruction. We ſhould take notice of the faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and admire it, and bleſs him for it. God is a faithful God, he is a never changing friend; alas we ſee amongſt men friends are falſe and fickle, and unfaithfull, they deal with us many times as <hi>Job</hi> complains his friends did. <hi>My bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren have dealt deceitfully as a brook.</hi> Job 6.15. a Brook that in the winter time hath rain enough, yet in the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150135:48"/>ſummer time, when the cattle ſtand in moſt need of water, then all the Brook is dried up; ſo ſaies he, my friends deal deceitfully with me, in the times of my diſtreſs and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and are then the furtheſt of all from me; and ſo <hi>David</hi> complains, Pſal. 38.11. <hi>My lovers and my friends ſtand a loof from my ſore, and my kinſmen ſtand afar off.</hi> But God is not ſuch a friend, God is never nearer to us, than when trouble is near; God never ſpeaks ſo kindly ſo comfortably, to the hearts of his children, as he doth when he brings them into a Wilderneſs, Hoſ. 2.14. <hi>Therefore behold I will allure her, and bring her into the Wilderneſs, and ſpeak comfortably unto her.</hi> When God brings us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the worſt condition, he is then the beſt God unto us; when we are in the ſaddeſt condition, we have many times the ſweeteſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with our God. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26. ſaies <hi>David, My fleſh and my heart faileth, but God is the ſtrength of my heart and my partion for ever.</hi> And that is a very comfortable paſſage of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150135:49"/>
               <hi>the Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſalm 142.3, 4, 5. <hi>When my Spirit was overwhelmed within me, then thou kneweſt my paths:</hi> When I was almoſt at my wits end ready to ſink down in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, then thou tookeſt notice of me: <hi>And I looked</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>on my right hand and beheld, but there was no man that would know me; refuge failed me, no man cared for my ſoul, then I cryed unto thee O Lord and ſaid, thou art my refuge and my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Land of the living.</hi> A wonderfull comfortable paſſage, and O! why do not we break out into admiration and ſay? O! God who, is like unto thee? who ſo loving a God, who ſo faithfull a God, who ſo tender hearted and compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate a Father as thou art, that ever owneſt thy children when they have moſt need of thee!</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>2</label> Another Uſe I would make of this Point is this, Doth God own us in the day of our fears, and ſtreights, and in the day of our dangers and diſtreſſes; and doth God own us before our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, then it ſhould teach us to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150135:49"/>own God before his enemies, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know ledge him before the worſt of men, and in the worſt of times.</p>
            <p>Firſt, We ſhould acknowledge God before the worſt of men, before Papiſts, or Atheifts, or Hereticks, or Seducers, or Hypocrites, or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, or ſcorners of Religion; for theſe are the worſt of his enemies. To own God before his freinds, this is no great matter, there is no ttryall in that, becauſe there is no oppoſition; but ſee what our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaies, <hi>Mar.</hi> 8.38. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my words in this adulterous and ſinfull generaton, of him alſo ſhall the Son of man be aſhamed when he cometh in the glory of his Father with the holy Angels.</hi> Our Saviour doth not ſay, whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me before a gracious generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for none will be aſhamed of Chriſt then; but whoſoever ſhall be aſh amed of me before an adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous generation. Though the men with whom we converſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom we live, be never ſo baſe, and vile, though they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150135:50"/>ſuch backſliding, provoking, ſcandalous, prophane wretches, and ſuch as are oppoſers of God, his truth and Goſpel; yet our Saviour looks we ſhould own him before theſe men, even before an adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous generation, elſe he will not own us at the great and dreadfull day of his appearing. Thus you ſhall ſee <hi>Paul</hi> owned Jeſus Chriſt before <hi>Nero,</hi> that bloody Monſter of men, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. <hi>At my firſt anſwer no man ſtood with me.</hi> I hat is, when he appeared before <hi>Nero;</hi> yet notwithſtanding <hi>Paul</hi> ſtood for God then; and God ſtood by <hi>Paul.</hi> Thus <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>John</hi> owned Jeſus Chriſt before <hi>Annas,</hi> and <hi>Caiphas,</hi> and before the Prieſt, and Rulers, and all thoſe that were the deſparate enimies, of the Goſpel, though they threatned, and impriſoned them. <hi>We cannot but ſpeak the things which we have ſeen and heard.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And then God looks that we ſhould own him, not onely before the worſt of men, but in the worſt of times; to own God in good times it is no great matter; Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150135:50"/>can own God in good times, but God looks we ſhould own him in times of apoſtacy, when Religion growes out of cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; when it is lookt upon as mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as Moroſitie, as Hypocriſie, and I know not what. God owns us when others forſake us, and therefore God looks that we ſhould own him when others forſake him. Thus you ſhall ſee <hi>Elijah</hi> did, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19.10. when there was ſuch a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall apoſtacy, that he thought there had not been a godly man left in <hi>Iſrael</hi> beſides himſelf; ſaies he, <hi>I onely am left, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I have been very jealous for the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kin. 18.40.</note> And very jealous indeed he was, for at one time he ſlew, and cauſed to be ſlain, no leſſe than four hundred of <hi>Jeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> falſe Prophets. I confeſs that act of <hi>Elijahs</hi> was an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary act, and much like that of <hi>Phinehas,</hi> one of the High Prieſts, that ſlew <hi>Zimry,</hi> and <hi>Cozby</hi> in his zeal for God, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.8. Doubtleſs this act of <hi>Phinehas,</hi> was alſo an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary act, and by Divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150135:51"/>as judicious <hi>Calvin</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves; but though their actions be not to be imitated, yet their zeal is worthy imitation: for <hi>Elijah</hi> owned God when none ſtood by him.</p>
            <p>And as we ſhould own God in times of apoſtacy, ſo in times of oppoſition. When there is a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate contention againſt the truth, we ſhould earneſtly contend, <hi>contend as in an agony,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> for the truth; as I once opened that Text to you, the Epiſtle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 3. The more violent men are againſt the truth, the more valiant we ſhould be for it; and the more outragious, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are in wayes of ſin, the more couragious ſhould we be in wayes of holineſs; the more others oppoſe Religion, and Reformation, and the power of godlineſs, the more ſhould we hold forth the word of truth; and hold faſt the word of life, by an undaunted reſolution. Thus the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> did, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remi.</hi> 6.10, 11. <hi>The word of the Lord is to them a reproach</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>They have no delight in it, therefore
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150135:51"/>I am full of the fury of the Lord, I am weary with holding in,</hi> and <hi>Act.</hi> 17.16. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls</hi> Spirit was ſtirred, it waxed hot within him, when he ſaw the <hi>Athenians,</hi> wholly given to Idolatry.</p>
            <p>And God looks we ſhould own him and his cauſe, not onely in times of apoſtacy, and in times of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and oppoſition againſt the truth, but in times of danger and perſecution, if he ſhould call us to ſuffer for it. Thus did the Martyrs, and O! that ſome of that holy fire, and zeal of love to God; that burnt in their breſts, were kindled in the hearts of every one of us. The godly Martyrs in the Primitive times, and in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies, carried the truth as it were in their armes, in the midſt of accuſations, perſecutions, ſlanders, reproaches; and in the defence of the truth, they were contented to paſſe through honour, and diſhonour, through evil report, and good report; Nay through bonds, and impriſonments, through racks and whips, through fire, and flames; and all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150135:52"/>and miſchief that earth, and hell could invent, and all the power that the devil, and darkneſs could raiſe againſt them could not quench, but rather kindled their zeal, O! that we had (I ſay) ſome of thoſe ſparks that burnt in their breaſts. Many there are that ſe em to own God and Religion, and his cauſe, and truth in calme and quiet times, when their profeſſion coſts them nothing: but as thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> that one day cryed <hi>Hoſanna, bleſſed is he that comes in the name of the Lord,</hi> the next day cryed, Crucifie him, Crucifie him, away with him, away with him. So likwiſe the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame profeſſors, if they be not ſound in the faith, that cry up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in times of proſperity, will cry down Religion in times of adverſity. Many there are that will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to follow Chriſt to Mount <hi>Olivet;</hi> I but they will not follow him to Mount <hi>Calvariſt,</hi> to ſuffer any thing with him, or indure any thing for him; no, Chriſt ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, and his cauſe, and truth ſhall ſuffer, and Religion, and reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150135:52"/>and all ſhall ſuffer rather than they will ſuffer with him. As the King of <hi>Navarre,</hi> once ſaid to <hi>Beza; In matters of Religion, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, I will lanch no farther into the Sea, than I may be ſure to return ſafe back again to Land.</hi> O! this is the temper of many men, but let it not be ours, let us be rowing though it be againſt wind, and tide; let us reſolve with <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 119.31. <hi>I will ſtick unto thy teſtimonies.</hi> I am <hi>glewed</hi> unto thy truth; ſo the Hebrew word ſignifies, ſo glewed that nothing ſhall draw me off,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or drive me from it, <hi>David</hi> was one that did indeed ſtick unto the word of God admirably; ſometimes he was derided, and ſcorned for the truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.51. <hi>The proud have had me greatly in deriſion, yet have I not declined from thy Law;</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.12. The drunkards made a ſong of him, yet did he not decline from the Law of God; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times again he was plundered and ſpoiled, and loſt much of his eſtate for ſticking to the truth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.61. <hi>The bands of the wicked have
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150135:53"/>robbed me, yet have I not forgotten thy Law.</hi> And he was not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided, and ſcorned, and plundered, but he was perſecuted too; <hi>ver.</hi> 161. <hi>Princes have perſecuted me without a cauſe, but my heart stands in awe of thy word:</hi> here was a man that ſtuck to God and his truth whatſoever he ſuffered. And O that the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution were fixed in our hearts that was in the heart of holy <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.8. <hi>We can do nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth but for the truth.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, though all the world ſpeak againſt the truth; though they ſhould band and binde themſelves againſt it, yet we cannot ſpeak againſt the truth, but muſt ſpeak for it, and plead for it, and die for it, if we be called to it. This is to own God when he owns us; and if we can thus own God, and his cauſe and truth, certainly we ſhall never be loſers by him, though for the preſent we may be loſers for him, for we ſerve a Maſter that will make up all our loſſes. And this is the ſecond Uſe.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, (to ſhut up this
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150135:53"/>Point with a word of Conſolation) Doth God acknowledge and own his people in the day of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and diſtreſſes? then here is a word of unſpeakable comfort to all that are true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, thoſe that ſtick to God, and his truth and teſtimonies; for if God do own and acknowledge us here on earth, then certainly he will much more own and acknowledge us at the great day of Chriſts appearing, when the wicked would give the whole world for one ſmile of his countenance,<note place="margin">Luke 23.30.</note> 
               <hi>when they ſhall cry to the mountains to fall on them, and to the hils to cover them and hide them, from the wrath of the Lamb;</hi> when their hearts ſhall fail them for fear, and looking for thoſe dreadfull things that are falling on them, ſaies Chriſt, even at that time <hi>do you lift up your heads with joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 21.26.28.</note> 
               <hi>for the day of your redemption draws nigh.</hi> God the Father will own his people at that day, when he will put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the righteous and the wicked, between them that fear him, and them that fear him not;<note place="margin">Mal. 3.18.</note>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:150135:54"/>and will ſay as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.13, 14. <hi>Behold my ſervants ſhall eat but ye ſhall be hungry, behold my ſervants ſhall drink but ye ſhall be thirsty, behold my ſervants ſhall rejoyce but ye ſhall be aſhamed, behold my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and howl for vexation of spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as God the Father will own them, ſo Jeſus Chriſt will own them at that great day. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall confeſs me before men, him will I confeſs alſo before my Father which is in heaven, and he that overcomes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rev. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>I will confeſs his name before my Father and before his holy Angels</hi> Jeſus Chriſt at that great day will viſibly own all his ſervants that have owned him, and owned his cauſe, and will ſay, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe are my ſervants, theſe are my friends, theſe are my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nay theſe are my Jewels;<note place="margin">Mat. 25.35, 36.</note> when I was hungry in my members, they fed me; when I was thirſty they gave me drink; when I was naked in my poor members on earth, they cloathed me; when I was
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150135:54"/>ſick they viſited me; when I was in priſon they came and relieved me:<note place="margin">Mat 25.35, 36.</note> and Father here is a man that laid down his eſtate for me, and was content to be plundered and ſpoyled ſo he might but keep his integrity: and here is another loſt his credit for me, and was content to be revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and reproached, and to be counted the off-ſcouring of all things for me: nay here is another laid down his very life for me; he loved not his life to the death, but was contented to part with his life rather than to part with the peace of a good conſcience. Father, all theſe have ſtuck to me, theſe are they that have borne me company, and have continued with me in the times of my temptations; they have ſtood to me in the hour of tryal, and have kept thy Word;<note place="margin">Luke 21.28. John 17.6, 9, 10.</note> they have kept their integrity and their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments clean, therefore Father theſe are thine: nay theſe are mine, for mine are thine, and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them: they have glorified me, and let them be glorified with me: <hi>Father I will that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150135:55"/>thoſe whom thou haſt given me may be with me where I am, that they may behold my glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 24.</note> O what an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable comfort will this be to all you (I ſay) that are willing thus to own Jeſus Chriſt, and his cauſe and truth, though in a ſinfull genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though it be in times of apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy and oppoſition of the truth, or in times of trouble and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the truth; if you can own Chriſt he will own you. And ſo much for the firſt thing, by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that was tendered to this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>I will acknowledge them</hi> (ſaies God) <hi>that are carried away captive of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond particular wherein God ſpeaks to them by way of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort is this, namely that <hi>he</hi> had ſent them out of this place into the Land of the <hi>Caldeans; I have ſent them</hi> (ſaies God,) as if he ſhould ſay, true indeed <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> carried them away captive, but he was but my inſtrument, I was the author of their captivity; <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> was the rod wherewith I chaſtiſed them, I but it was my hand ruled the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150135:55"/>rod. Now the Doctrine I would commend to you from hence is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That whoever are the inſtruments of our miſeries and calamities,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>yet God is the author of them.</hi> Amos 3.6. <hi>Shall there be evil in a City and the Lord hath not done it?</hi> he ſpeaks not of the evil of ſinne (for certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God is not the author of ſinne, that is a blaſphemous doctrine to make God the author of ſinne) but he ſpeaks of the evil of puniſhment; and this is the doctrine <hi>Eliphaz</hi> taught <hi>Job,</hi> Job 5.6. <hi>Affliction com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not forth of the dust, neither doth trouble ſpring out of the ground:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, Do not think O <hi>Job,</hi> that it is chance or Fortune that doth toſs or tumble things upſide down here below, as if God were an idle ſpectator in Heaven, and were doing nothing there; no, ſaies he, but God fits in Heaven, and he is at the ſterne and ſteers all the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this world as it pleaſeth him: and all the afflictions that have ever befallen thee, come not by chance, but by the wiſe diſpoſing hand of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150135:56"/>God: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.7. ſaies God, <hi>I form the light and create darkneſs, I make peace and create evil, I the Lord do all theſe things.</hi> And this is the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>Job</hi> had learnt, <hi>Job</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord gave and the Lord hath taken away.</hi> The Lord hath taken away, may ſome ſay; why was it not the <hi>Sabeans,</hi> and the <hi>Caldeans</hi> that robd <hi>Job?</hi> they took away his Sheep and Oxen, and they ſlew his ſervants with the edg of the ſword. I but <hi>Job</hi> looks not at them, it is the Lord (ſaies he) that gave me all my ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and 'tis he that hath taken them all away. And <hi>David</hi> he had learnt this leſſon;<note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>Shimei</hi> railed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him with a black mouth, and ſaid, <hi>Come out, come out thou bloody man and thou man of Belial: Abiſhai</hi> would have been avenged of him preſently, and would have taken off <hi>the head of that dead dog</hi> (as he call'd him) no, no, ſaies <hi>David, The Lord hath ſent Shimei to curſe David:</hi> and if God hath once ſaid it, who ſhall ſay, wherefore haſt thou done ſo.</p>
            <p>For the Reaſon of this Doctrine, (that I may briefly wrap it up be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150135:56"/>I would not hold you long) it is this, becauſe God hath an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, independent, and unlimited Soveraignty over all creatures in Heaven and earth. This is the leſſon God would teach <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and he ſends him to the Potters houſe to learn it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.2, 3, 4. God ſaies God to the Potters houſe, and I will teach thee a leſſon; and <hi>Jeremiah</hi> goes, and he ſees the Potter making pots apace, and he no ſooner fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions one pot upon the wheel, but he breaks it to pieces preſently; and what doth God teach them by this? <hi>O houſe of Iſrael</hi> (ſaies God) <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not I do with you as this Potter with the clay?</hi> cannot I make of a piece of clay, one veſſel of honour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of diſhonour? cannot I ſave whom I will, and deſtroy whom I will? <hi>as the clay is in the hands of the Potter, ſo are ye in my hands O houſe of Iſrael,</hi> verſe the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>? and therefore he tells them in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſes, that it was in his power to do what he pleaſed: ſaies he, I can pull down Kingdoms, and I can plant Kingdoms; I can build
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150135:57"/>up Kingdoms, and I can throw down Kingdoms and Nations even as I pleaſe, like as the Potter can do by the clay. <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> a proud man would not learn this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to know he ruled by God, and that God was the abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of all creatures here below; therefore God ſends him to ſchool, not to the Potters houſe as he did <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> but he ſends him to the beaſts, and he graſes amongſt the Oxen, till he came to know that God ruled amongſt the children of men, and after ſeaven years he had learnt this leſſon, and makes an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable confeſſion, <hi>Daniel</hi> 4.35. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>this great God doth according to his own will in the army of Heaven, and amongſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the earth, and none can ſtay his hand, or ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me but briefly apply this Point, and then I will end: I have but three Uſes, and I will be very brief in every one of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By way of Inſtruction and Admonition. If God be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150135:57"/>of all the miſeries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that befall us here below: It ſhould then teach us this leſſon, to fear this great God that hath the rod in his hand, wherewith he can ſcourge whom he will, and where and how long he will, O! that you and I could learn to ſtand in awe of him, and be afraid to ſin againſt him, againſt <hi>him</hi> who can ſend the ſword, the famine and the Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to conſume us from off the face of the earth, as it is in the laſt verſe of this 24. Chapter of <hi>Jeremiah, I will ſend the ſword, the famine, and the Peſtilence among them, till they be conſumed from off the Land that I gave unto them, and to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi> So Jer. 10.6, 7. <hi>There is none O Lord like unto thee, thou art great, and thy name is great in might, who would not fear thee O King of Nations.</hi> And Jer. 15.22. <hi>Fear ye not me ſaith the Lord? will you not tremble at my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, who have placed the Sand for a girdle to the Sea, by a perpetuall decree that it cannot paſs it?</hi> What do you not fear me that can chain up that great Monſter the Sea in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150135:58"/>fetters of ſand? do you not fear me that can toſs the earth more eaſily than you can toſs a tennis ball? nay fear ye not me that can caſt ſoul and body into hell fire?<note place="margin">Mat. 10.28.</note> When there is a mighty Prince or Potentate, that hath power in his hands, to ſtrip you of your liberties, of your eſtates, and lives, and he is incenſed againſt you, O! what terrour and tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling takes hold of you, and how do you crouch, and cringe, and comply, and make friends, and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all the ways that ever you can, to get the favour of that Prince or Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, as you read Acts 12.20. When <hi>Herod</hi> was highly diſpleaſed with the men of <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon,</hi> they got <hi>Blastus</hi> the Kings Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine to be their friend, and beg tearms of peace for them. Now art thou afraid of a mortall man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrils, and art not afraid of the great Creator of heaven and earth Iſa. 51 12.13. <hi>Who art thou that art afraid of a man that ſhalldy, and of the Son of man which ſhall be made as graſs, and forgeteſt the Lord thy maker, that hath ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150135:58"/>forth the heavens, and laid the foundations of the earth.</hi> Conſider this all you that are great ones, or men of great eſtates, and therefore think you may bolſter up your ſelves in your wickedneſs, no, no, know thus much, this great <hi>Jehovah</hi> againſt whom you ſin, he is the great Lord; he is greater than the greateſt; it is he that <hi>can viſit</hi> with his anger, and with his fury, and with his indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion poured forth.<note place="margin">Nah. 1.5.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>The Mountains quake at him, and the hils melt, and the earth is burnt up at his preſence, yea the world and all that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: who can ſtand before his indignation, and who can abide in the fierceneſs of his anger? his fury is poured out like fire, and the rocks melt before him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 149.8.</note> It is he that can bind Kings in chains, and Nobles in fetters of iron. It is he that is the Lord of hoſts, that hath all creatures in heaven and earth, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his quarel: It is this great God likewiſe, that can puniſh great and ſmall, without reſpect of perſons: and therefore they on whom God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows great mercies, if they abound in great ſins, they ſhall have great
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150135:59"/>puniſhment inflicted upon them,<note place="margin">Potentes potentèr pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienter.</note> as one ſaid, <hi>Mighty men ſhall be mightily tormented.</hi> O whence is it that we no more fear this great God before whom the rocks melt, nay the devils tremble! Are our hearts harder than rocks? Are we more fearleſs than devils? Stand in awe then, and ſin not; moſt men ſin and tremble not, but do you tremble and ſin not. Conſider we are all in the hands of this great God, as a little fly in the paw of a roaring lion; we are all before him as clay in the hands of the Potter; nay we are all before him as dry ſtubble before the conſuming fire. Do we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to jealouſie? Are we ſtronger than he?<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.22.</note> Conſider what advantage he hath againſt us, and conſider alſo what dependance we have upon him, and then learn to ſear him, and to ſtand in awe of him. This is the firſt Uſe: it is the great God that hath the rod in his hand, and he is the Author of all the miſeries that come upon us, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us tremble before him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Uſe is for inſtruction,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150135:59"/>and admonition; If God be the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all the miſerie that befals us, then let us take off our eys from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and ſecond cauſes; look not ſo much at man, at the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our miſery, but look upon God who is the author of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. O that every one of us could but ſay as that good woman <hi>Naomi,</hi> Ruth 1.13. ſaies ſhe, <hi>the hand of the Lord is gone out againſt me.</hi> Could we but look at God the author, more than at the inſtruments of our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, we ſhould have great advantage by it. You will ſay what advantage; there is a fourfold advantage we ſhall have by it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This will work the ſweet effect of contentment and quietation in our hearts; it will meeken, and quiet, and calme our ſpirits, that we ſhall not fret and fume at any diſpenſation of God, though it ſeem never ſo harſh and ſevere. Pſal. 39.9. <hi>I was dumb, and opened not my mouth becauſe thou didſt it.</hi> and 1 Sam. 3.18. ſaies <hi>Eli</hi> (when a heavy meſſage came to him) <hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeemeth him good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:150135:60"/>Secondly, This will root out that ſpirit of revenge that uſually is in our hearts, when they are burning and boyling againſt thoſe that are the inſtruments of our miſery. We are many times like the Dog that ſnarles at the ſtone, and looks not at the hand that caſt it; ſo we ſnarl, and fret, and boyl in our ſpirits, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe who are the inſtruments of our troubles; whereas did we but look at the hand that caſt the ſtone, it would take the ſpirit of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge out of our hearts. Such a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was in <hi>David,</hi> as I ſhewed you even now, he looked not at <hi>Shimei</hi> curſing him, but at God that bid him curſe, and therefore would not be revenged on <hi>Shimei.</hi> Such a Spirit was in <hi>Joſeph</hi> Gen. 45.8. Saies he to his brethren, <hi>It was not you that ſent me hither, but God.</hi> Why, may ſome ſay, it was his brethren, for did not they ſell <hi>Joſeph</hi> to the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maelites,</hi> and by that means was he not carried into <hi>Egypt?</hi> I but <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> looks not to the inſtruments, but to God; and therefore though his brethren had miſgiving thoughts,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150135:60"/>ſurely our brother will remember this,<note place="margin">Gen. 50.15.</note> and be avenged on us for all the wrong we did him, yet <hi>Joſeph</hi> anſwers them otherwiſe, 'tis true ſales he, <hi>you intended evil to me, but God turned it for good;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be not troubled, I have no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge in my heart; and fear not, for I will nouriſh you, and your little ones. He lookt at God in all.</p>
            <p>And Thirdly, this will provoke us to repentance, and to return to God that ſmites us. Hoſ. 6.1. <hi>Come and let us return unto the Lord, for he hath torn, and he will heal us, he hath ſmitten, and he will bind us up.</hi> As in the caſe of mercies, if we do not look upon God as the author of our mercies, we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be thankfull and improve them to his Glory. So likewiſe in the caſe of afflictions, if we look not upon God, as the Author of our miſeries, we can never be penitent, and humble.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, We ſhall have this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage alſo; this will work our hearts to a patient and quiet waiting
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150135:61"/>upon God, with faith and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for deliverance. 2 King. 6.33. you read of King <hi>Jehoram,</hi> a prophane King, yet he taught a true doctrine, ſaies he, <hi>this evil is of the Lord.</hi> A true Doctrine, but he made a falſe uſe and application of it, <hi>therefore why ſhould I wait upon him any longer.</hi> For the reaſon holds ſtrong on the contrary ſide; this evil is from the Lord, therefore I ſhould wait upon him for ever. This is a good concluſion; for that God that hath ſmitten us will heal us, if we wait upon him; though he hide his face for a little while, yet he will not always hide his face;<note place="margin">Iſa. 57.16.</note> and though he contend for a little while, yet he will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end for ever, leſt the ſpirit which he hath made ſhould faile before him.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Uſe is for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation; Is God the Author of all the miſeries and calamities that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall us, then it ſerves for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the people of God in this, that God can order and overrule, and he can bridle and reſtrain wicked
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150135:61"/>and ungodly men, in all their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, in all their plots and projects, and in all their purpoſes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that they have againſt his people, becauſe he is the Author whoever be the inſtruments; all wicked men are but the rod in his hand, <hi>O Aſſyrian the rod of mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the ſtaff in their hand is mine indignation,</hi> Iſa. 10.5. and if there were twenty rods in a room, and never a hand to uſe one of them, we would not be afraid of them, the rod can do nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs their be a hand to uſe it, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments can do nothing if God do not make uſe of them, or if he do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain them. <hi>God can ſtill the rage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſea, the noiſe of their waves, and the tumult of the people,</hi> Pſal. 65.7. and theſe two are joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, the raging of the Sea, and the tumnlt of the people; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying thus much, that though people ſhould rage againſt Gods ſervants, as much as the waves of th Sea, yet God can reſtrain them; he that ſaies to the waves, thus far ſhall ye go and no further, here
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150135:62"/>ſhall your proud waves be ſtayed, he can ſay to the rage and fury of the greateſt oppreſſours upon earth, thus far ſhall ye go and no further; that God that doth whatſoever pleaſeth him in heaven and earth, he will order things ſo that we may be fure though his Church be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, yet it ſhall not be ſupreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and if he can do whatſoever pleaſeth him,<note place="margin">Pſa. 31.15.</note> then the enemies of the Church cannot do whatſoever pleaſeth them. My times are in thy hands ſaies <hi>David:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 115.7.</note> truly if the times of our troubles were in our own hands the rod would be taken away too ſoon, and if our times were in our enemies hands, our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions would be too long, but now becauſe our times are in Gods hands, therefore he will order and over-rule both for time and manner, and meaſure, ſo as may make moſt for the glory of his own Name, and for our comfort, that though he do humble us, and prow us, yet it is, that he may do us good in the latter end.</p>
            <p>And this leads me to the third
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150135:62"/>and laſt particular in the Text, The third comfort that is tendered to theſe poor Captives, ſaies God here, <hi>I have ſent them out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans, but it is for their good,</hi> for their ſpirituall benefit, and advantage. But of that God willing you ſhall hear in the after noon, ſo much ſhall ſerve for this time.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:150135:63"/>
            <head>SERMON IV.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jeremiah Chap. 24. Verſe 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, the God of Iſrael, Like theſe good Figs, ſo will I acknowledge them that are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away captive of Judah, whom I have ſent out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have ſpoken to this Text (as you may remember) in three Sermons, I will by Gods aſſiſtance fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh it at this time. I have done with the explication of the Type, <hi>like theſe good Figs,</hi> and am now upon the application if it; and the application is wholly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and that in three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:150135:63"/>Firſt, God tels them that he would <hi>acknowledge</hi> them that were carried away (aptive of <hi>Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly, That <hi>he himſelf</hi> had ſent them into the Land of the <hi>Caldeans:</hi> and theſe two I have diſpatched.</p>
            <p>I come now to the third and laſt particular, and that which is moſt remarkable in the Text, and that is, that God doth aſſure them here, that this their captivity ſhould be for their <hi>good,</hi> for their ſpirituall profit and advantage; <hi>I have ſent them out of this place into the Land of the Caldeans for their good.</hi> And the Point of Doctrine, I would commend to you from hence is this,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God in the ſevereſt of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viences,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>and the ſharpeſt afflictions that his people meet withall, doth yet intend their ſpirituall good.</hi> To be carried captive into <hi>Babylon,</hi> doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it was a very ſevere providence and a very ſharp affliction, if you conſider either the antecedents of it, or the conſequents of it; the antecedents of it, what went before;
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150135:64"/>why blood and ſlaughter, and the loſs of many mens lives; or if you conſider alſo the conſequents of it, what followed their captivitie, why the enſlaving of their perſons, the loſs of their eſtates, the leaving of their Country, and the Land of their nativity; the ſcorns and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, the exultations and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs of their adverſaries that would be ready to trample upon their miſery, whereas miſery ſhould be a loadſtone for mercy, and not a footſtool for pride to trample up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but yet this they muſt look for, to be trampled upon and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpht over by their inſulting ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries: as for example, the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domites</hi> ſaid in the day of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> (that is, in the day of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems</hi> miſery,) <hi>Down with it, down with it even to the ground,</hi> Pſal. 137.7. Yea they rejoyced over the Children of <hi>Judah</hi> in the day of their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and they ſpake proudly in the day of their diſtreſs, as it is in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Obadiah,</hi> v. 12. So likwiſe the <hi>Amonites,</hi> you ſhall ſee how they inſulted over them, when they
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150135:64"/>had carried them Captive, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26.6. ſaies God, <hi>Thou haſt clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped thine hands, and ſtamped with the feet, and rejoyced in heart with all thy deſpite againſt the Land of Iſrael,</hi> Inſomuch that the people of God complain, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 44.13. <hi>O Lord thou makeſt us a reproach to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, a ſcorn and a deriſion to them that are round about us.</hi> Theſe were the wofull conſequences of that Captivitie, and yet, God ſaies not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he did intend their ſpirituall good. This is that which God tels them. <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.41. <hi>Yea I will rejoyce over you to do you good, and I will plant you in this Land aſſuredly, with my whole heart, and with my wholeſoul.</hi> And how many teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies might I produce to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that God in the ſevereſt of his diſpenſations, doth yet intend his Childrens good, <hi>Dut.</hi> 8.15, 16. <hi>When he led thee through that great and terrible Wilderneſs, wherein were fiery Serpents, and Scorpions, and drought, where there was no water</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It was that he might humble thee and prove thee, that he might do thee
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150135:65"/>good at thy latter end.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. 'tis a known Scripture, and as comfortable a Scripture as any in all the Book of God, <hi>We know that all things work togather for good to them that love God, to them who are the called according to his purpoſe.</hi> And <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.10. <hi>He chaſtiſeth us for our profit that we might be partakers of his holineſs.</hi> And hear but <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> out of his own experience, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.71, 75, v. <hi>It is good for me that I have been afflicted, that I might learn thy ſtatutes, and I know O Lord that in very faithfullneſs thou haſt afflicted me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for the better confirmation, and explication of this truth (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a truth that fleſh and blood will hardly believe, that God in his ſevereſt providences ſhould intend our good) There are theſe three queries that would be ſatiſſied.</p>
            <p>Frſt, What good it is that God doth intend in his ſevereſt providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces towards his Children?</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, Who they are that ſhall experimently find this Doctrine verified of them?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:150135:65"/>And thirdly, How or with what limitation this Doctrine muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood?</p>
            <p>Friſt, What good it is that God doth intend his people? Briefly there is a fourfold good, that God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends unto his people in his correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and chaſtiſements, and in the wayes of his ſeverity towards them. 1. In reference to their ſins. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> In reference to their graces. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to their preſent comforts, 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> In reference to their future hopes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reference to their ſins, God intends a fourfold good; 1. To prevent ſin. 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> To diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſin. 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> To imbitter ſin. And 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> To deſtory ſin.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God in reference to the ſins of his people intends this good to them, namely to prevent ſin: If Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſuch a heavenly man, or an earthly Angel (as one cals him) had need of a thorne in his fleſh, to prevent that ſpirituall pride, and ſelf exaltation, that otherwiſe he might have fallen into? O How much more have we need of ſome
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150135:66"/>affiction, to prevent thoſe ſins that otherwiſe we might run into? That as Phyſitians tell us, they have two ſorts of medecines, They have Preventing Phyſick,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> as well as healing Phyſick; ſo God makes afflictions to be preventing Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, as well as healing Phyſick, unto his own Children. And as <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſaid in the like caſe,<note place="margin">Periiſſem niſt Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſem.</note> 
               <hi>If I had not been undone I had been undone;</hi> So may many a child of God ſay; if God had not hedged up my way with Thornes, I had run poſt to the pit of hell, and had ruſhed upon the rock of my own ruin long before this time. That is one good in reference to ſin to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Another good God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his people by afflictions, in reference to their ſin, is to diſcover it; in ſtanding waters you cannot ſee the mud that lies at the bottom of the Pool; but when once the water is removed, then the mud is diſcovered. So here, while we are at peace, and caſe, in times of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and whiles we are not emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150135:66"/>from veſſel to veſſel, we are ſetled upon our lees, as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Moab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 48.11.</note> and the dregs and mud of our corruptions are not diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but now when we are empti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from veſſel to veſſel, that is, emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied of our outward enjoyments, and of our outward comforts, and God begins to take the rod into his hand, then he makes us reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, and to ſay as <hi>Job</hi> did in the day of his diſtreſs, <hi>Job</hi> 13.23, 24. <hi>Make me to know my tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion and my ſin.</hi> Remarkeable is that ſpeach of the <hi>Shunamitiſh</hi> wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man unto <hi>Elijah</hi> 1 King. 17.18. <hi>Art thou come to call my ſin to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance and to ſlay my ſon?</hi> Pray marke, the death of her ſon made her reflect upon her ſin, ſhe would not have called her ſin to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, but that her ſon was now rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be taken away; affliction it is a ſharp tyrant, I but it is a juſt judge, it repreſents our condition truly to us, and lets us ſee the inſide of our ſelves, it doth diſcover ſelf to ſelf: a man never comes to know himſelf, and to know the plague of his own
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:150135:67"/>heart, ſo well as when the rod of God is upon his back; that is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond good afflictions work in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ſin, to diſcover it.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, God intends this good to his people in reference to ſin, to imbitter it, that in the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſorrow, we may taſt the bitterneſs of ſin, that is the cauſe of ſorrow, that we may ſee and ſay as in <hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.19. <hi>'Tis an evill and bitter thing, that we have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Lord our God, and that his fear hath not been in us.</hi> And brethren, ſin it is a very bitter thing, nay ſin is bitterneſs it ſelf; <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im hath provoked him to anger moſt bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly,</hi> in the Hebrew it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ephraim</hi> hath provoked him with <hi>bitterneſſes:</hi> Sin it is that which cauſed the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to drink that bitter cup of trembling. It would have made all the men on earth, nay all the Angels in heaven to have ſunk under the burden of that wrath that he drunk of, ſo that ſin is I ſay a bitter thing; and therefore God afflicts us, to imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſin to us, and that we ſhould be
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150135:67"/>in bitterneſs for ſin as a man is in bitterneſs for the loſs of an onely childe.<note place="margin">Zech. 12.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And then fourthly, In refrence to ſin, God afflicts us to deſtroy ſin, to make a ſeparation between ſin and the ſoul. A ſucking child that loves the mothers breaſt, yet (you know) when Worm-wood is laid upon the breaſt, then the child loaths it, and is willing to leave it, and it becomes but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a dead breaſt to him, though before he delighted in it. So likewiſe, when God is pleaſed to imbitter ſin, he doth as it were kill the ſin to us, and makes us willing to leave it, though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we did dearly love it; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is but fit and equall, that that ſin which hath been contracted with joy, ſhould be diſſolved with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: ſin is ſo rooted, and ſetled in the heart, that a ſeparation cannot be made without a great deal of ſorrow, but when once we feel the ſmart of ſin, then we can ſay with holy <hi>Job,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 34.32.</note> 
               <hi>That which I know not, teach thou me; and if I have done iniquity, I will doe no more.</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:150135:68"/>And (ſaies he) <hi>Once have I ſpoken, but I will not anſwer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 40.5.</note> 
               <hi>yea twice, but I will proceed no farther.</hi> This then is the firſt Good God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his Children in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of his providences, in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ſin, to prevent it, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, imbitter it, and deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>But then ſecondly, God intends another good unto his people in the ſevereſt of his providences, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to their graces, both to try their graces, and likewiſe to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their graces.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To try their graces; God he ſometimes proves and tries his Chidren, whether they be legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Children, or whether they be baſtards, yea or no, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.10. <hi>For thou O God haſt proved us, thou haſt tryed us, as ſilver is tryed.</hi> And <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.8. <hi>If yea be without chaſtiſement, whereof all are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, than are ye baſtards, and not ſons.</hi> As they ſay of the Eagit, ſhee tries her young ones, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their eyes againſt the bright and ſcorching beames of the Sun
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150135:68"/>and if they cannot endure thoſe ſcorching beames, ſhe rejects them as ſpurious and as a baſtardly brood. So God ſomtimes tries his Children, to ſee whether they will be conſtant, or no, and whether they be his own Children, or ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards. And ſo he tries their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess whether they be golden graces. <hi>Re v.</hi> 3.18. <hi>I counſell thee to buy of me gold, tryed in the fire.</hi> 'Tis a Text I once opened to you, and I ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you by gold there, is ment the golden graces of the Spirit of God: and pray mark, our Saviour would have ſuch gold as is tryed in the fire; implying thus much, that our graces are not true graces, unleſs they be able to hold out in the day of tryall, and tribulation; gold (you know) will endure the fire: The Apoſtle ſpeaking of our faith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. ſaies <hi>The very tryall of it is much more precious then gold that periſheth.</hi> And if the tryall of it be ſo precious, what will the victory, or conqueſt of it be? As one ſaies, <hi>Some vertues, and graces, they are like Stars that
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150135:69"/>ſhine not in the day time of proſperity, but ſhine onely in the night of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi> We had never known <hi>Jobs</hi> patience, had not we known <hi>Jobs</hi> ſufferings. As their is Honey you know in the comb, but it comes not out uſually till it be preſt: and as there is ſweet water in the Roſe leaf, but it comes not out till it be fired: and as the ſtrength of a Tower is not known till an aſſault, and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery be made againſt it; So there are many graces in a Chriſtian that will never be diſcovered till the day of affliction.</p>
            <p>And as the Lord afflicts us for the tryall of our graces; ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the exerciſe of our graces; faith would not be exerciſed, were it not for afflictions, <hi>We know not what to doe, but our eyes are toward thee,</hi> 2 Chron. 20.12. And pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would not be exerciſed were it not for afflictions,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.3.</note> and therefore the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>Tribulations worke pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</hi> And obedience would not be exerciſed were it not for afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it is ſaid of our Saviour,<note place="margin">Hebr. 5.8.</note> that <hi>He learnt obedience by the things
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150135:69"/>which he ſuffered.</hi> A man trained up in the ſchool of affliction will gain more good by one Sermon than another will gain by ten, for in times of proſperity, we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have a deafe ear; ſome truths we underſtand not, others we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not; we kick at ſome truths and fret at others; but affliction opens the ear for diſcipline.<note place="margin">Job 36.10.</note> And ſo ſervent prayer would not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed were it not for afflictions <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.16. <hi>Lord in trouble have they viſited thee, they pouered out a prayer when thy chaſtening was upon them;</hi> They prayed to purpoſe then. A man may pray in times of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but he ſeldome pouers out a prayer till affliction comes; as One ſaies, <hi>Prayer without afflictions is but like a bird without wings.</hi> 'Tis ſaid of our bleſſed Saviour, when he was in an agonie he prayed a great deal the more earneſtly; So that afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on adds much to the grace of prayer. And our ſimpathy likewiſe towards our bretheren, would not be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, like afflictions work like af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; neither would our fear
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150135:70"/>of the great and holy name of God be exerciſed; ſo that affllictions are both for the tryall and for the exerciſes of our graces.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Another good God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends by afflictions, is in reference to our preſent comſorts and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that we may not ſurfer upon the lucious contentments here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; therefore in the midſt of our comforts, God gives us ſome croſſes to diet us, as in the midſt of our croſſes he gives us ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to ſupport us; the Lord knows that we have weak heads, and are not able to bear a proſperous eſtate without ſome bitter ingredient. If any of you have a Child, that hath but a weak head, and he is drinking wine &amp; one comes and mingles a little water with the wine, you thank him for it, becauſe your poor Child is not able to bear ſtrong drink, &amp; therefore it is a great favour to have ſome wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mingled with it. God I ſay ſees that we are not able to bear a proſperous eſtate, and therefore it is a great mercie that he mingles ſome affliction with it, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150135:70"/>by imbitters our comforts, and ſo ſeaſons our joys, that we may not ſurfet with them; and indeed one main end, that God aims at in all our afflictions, is to imbitter all outward things to us, that himſelf alone may be ſweet to our poor ſouls. God would not have us ſet our hearts upon things here below, he would not have theſe outward comforts to ſteal away our hearts, as <hi>Abſolom</hi> ſtole away the hearts of the people, nor would he have us ſay as <hi>Peter</hi> did, it is good being here, or to ſet up our ſtaff here, but to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with what we do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, and to contemn it in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what we do expect. That is a third thing in reference to our preſent comforts.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Another good God intends likewiſe, is in reference to our future hopes, for theſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, theſe ſevere diſpenſations of his providence, they are both the way to Glory, and they work out our Glory; they are the way to Glory, Luke 24.26. <hi>Ought not Chriſt to have ſuffered theſe things.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150135:71"/>and ſo to enter into his Glory.</hi> What hath the head gone that way, and muſt not the member go the ſame way alſo. Nay they work out our Glory, 2 Cor 4.17. <hi>for our light affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of Glory.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions they are but the file where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with God doth poliſh and ſquare us, that we may be fit ſtones in his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall building. Thus you ſee the firſt thing opened unto you, what Good God intends, in the ſevereſt of his diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, Who are they to whom God intends this good, certainly God doth not intend it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Figs, he never intended it to the wicked, but he intends it to thoſe that are good Figs as it is here in the text.</p>
            <p>I but how ſhall we do to know we are good Figs? I gave you three Characters you may remember the laſt Lords day, let me very briefly give you but three more now, that ſo you may know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be thoſe good Figs to
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:150135:71"/>whom this promiſe belongs, that all the ſevere diſpenſations of God ſhall be for your good.</p>
            <p>Firſt, If you be upright in heart Pſal. 125.4. <hi>Do good O Lord unto thoſe that be good,</hi> I but who are they, he tels you in the next words, <hi>to them that are upright in their hearts.</hi> If you be good not only in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance but good in proof, if you be good in reality, for you know rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Figs may make as fair a ſhew as the beſt Figs, they may be as big as the beſt, and poſſibly of as good a colour, I but yet they are rotten with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. If you have not only an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, for that is an eaſie matter; but if with your outward profeſſion, and giving up of your names to Chriſt, you joyn an inward ſubmiſſion, and give up your hearts to Chriſt, that you <hi>obey from the heart,</hi> as it is Rom. 6.17. then are you theſe good Figs to whom God intends good in all your afflictions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If you have a filial fear of God, and can fear him for his goodneſs, mark that text Jer. 32.40, 41. Saies God, <hi>I will put my
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:150135:72"/>fear into their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from me;</hi> And then ſaies he, <hi>I will rejoyce over them to do them good, with my whole heart, and with my whole ſoul.</hi> If God have put this fear into your hearts, and this fear is a fountain of life, to cauſe you to depart from the ſnares of death, then are you theſe good Figs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If you be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe that love God, and are called according to his purpoſe; For that is ſet dewn <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>And we know that all things worke together for good, to them that love God, and are called ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ording to his purpoſe.</hi> If you love his ordinances, and love his Saints and children, and love his preſence, if you love him for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and delight in him, and deſire him only, that you can ſay, none but thy ſelf O Lord, can give my ſoul ſatisfaction; and can ſay with <hi>Luther, Do not put me eff with theſe earthly comforts and contentments: It is not an houſefull of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that I can take up with, but I
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150135:72"/>muſt have thy ſelf, and the ſmiles of thy face, and the diſcoveries of thy love, and nothing elſe.</hi> And if you are called, according to his purpoſe, that is,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.14.</note> not only outwardly called by his word (for ſo <hi>many are called but few are choſen</hi>) but inwardly called by his Spirit, for you muſt know this promiſe doth not belong to every one that is outwardly called on; a man may be outwardly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but yet not effectually called; there is an outward ordinary gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall invitation that a wicked man may have, when the Spirit of God knocks at his heart by his word, by his mercies, by afflictions, and by the examples of others, and he ſtifles all the motions of the Spirit, and rejects the offers and tenders of his Grace, now to have onely this Generall invitation, it is not to be truly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for ſo the Spirit knocks of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at the doors of your hearts in many a Sermon, and in many a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and in many purpoſes of heart; I but now if you are called by the effectuall operation of the Spirit of God, that the Spirit of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150135:73"/>God not onely knocks but unlocks the doors of your hearts, and makes you willing to accept the invitations of his grace, and to give entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto Chriſt, and you can ſay come Lord Jeſus into my heart, and rule in me as thou pleaſeſt, when he ſo calls, that you hear his voyce, and when he ſaies <hi>Seek</hi> ye my face, thy heart anſwers, Lord thy face I will ſock, <hi>Come unto me</hi> (ſaies Chriſt) <hi>all yea that labour and are heavy laden,</hi> Math. 11.28. And the heart re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns eccho, come, I would come to thee O bleſſed Saviour upon my hands and knees, I would come with all my ſoul: when the Spirit of God ſaies, this is the way, this is the way of holineſſe, this is the way of ſtrictneſſe, and purity, ſo much ſpoken againſt every where: Is this the way ſaies a poor ſoul: O! I would walk in it, that I might find reſt to my ſoul, and I would ſubmit to the Government of Jeſus Chriſt and be as willing to have him my Ruler as my Redeemer, if thou loveſt God, and haſt choſen him for thy portion, and art thus
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150135:73"/>called, and returneſt an eccho to the voice of Chriſt, and ſubmits to his Government; this is a certain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence thou art in the number of thoſe the Text here ſpeaks of, whom God intends good to in his ſevereſt dipenſations. That is the ſecond thing by way of explication.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, With what limitations muſt this be underſtood, that God in his ſevereſt providences intends his peoples good? There are but theſe two limitations I will give you, and then I will apply all.</p>
            <p>Firſt, When 'tis ſaid God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends his peoples good, you muſt underſtand it thus; That this good is not preſently, and all at once ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, but it is by degrees. It may be for the preſent, thou findeſt no benefit at all by thy afflictions, but thy heart in thy own apprehenſion is rather made barder, and thou ſits down in a diſconſolate deſpondency, and doſt not ſee how ſuch a paſſage of providence workes for thy good at all; I but mark what the end will be; look not onely at the beginning of a work, (ſaies <hi>Solomon</hi>) but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150135:74"/>the end of it; give God leave to do his own work,<note place="margin">Ecl. 7.8.</note> and give him leave to do it his own way, and give him leave to do it in his own time, ſaies the Apoſtle, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.11. <hi>You have ſeen the end the Lord made with Job.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37. <hi>Mark the perfect man and behold the upright, for the end of that man is peace.</hi> And <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.16. <hi>He humbled thee, and proved thee, to do thee good at thy latter end.</hi> He doth not ſay it was to doe them good pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently; but to doe them good how ever in the latter end, with this limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation therefore it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, though for the preſent, thou maiſt not find it ſo, yet in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion thou ſhalt find it ſo.</p>
            <p>Again ſecondly, Another limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is this, when we ſay that all theſe providences of God ſhall worke for good; you muſt not underſtand them ſingly and apart, but taken joyntly and together, and ſo they will be for good:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> this is that which is expreſt <hi>Rom</hi> 8.28. <hi>All things work together for good;</hi> they work <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:</hi> if thou ſhouldeſt take one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence alone, by it ſelfe, haply thou
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150135:74"/>maiſt find it do thee no good at all, but now put providences together, and then thou wilt find them do thee good; as one drug in an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries Shop, cannot make a wholeſome medicine, but put many drugs together, and then it will do thee good: And one wheel in the Clock (you know) cannot make the Clock move, but put all the wheels together,<note place="margin">Gen. 42.36.</note> and then it will move. <hi>Jacob</hi> complains (ſaies he) <hi>Joſeph is not, and Simion is not, and ye will take Benjamen away, all theſe things are againſt me.</hi> True, take theſe providences ſingly by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and they were all againſt him; I but at laſt he had his <hi>Joſeph</hi> again, and his <hi>Simeon</hi> again, and his <hi>Benjamin</hi> again, and though for the preſent they were all againſt him, yet he loſt nothing in the latter end.</p>
            <p>Now for the Uſe of this Point briefly:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> If God in his ſevereſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations intend his peoples good, we may learn then theſe, four leſſons by way of Inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Learn to admire the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite wiſdome of God; that ſame
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:150135:75"/>various,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> curious wiſdome of God the Apoſtles ſpeak of, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.10. that can bring light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; peace out of trouble; good out of evil; grace out of ſin; hope out of fear; and heaven out of hell. O! the unſpeakable wiſdome of God; here is <hi>Samſons</hi> riddle now expounded, out of the eater God can bring forth meat, and out of the ſtrong God can bring forth ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, out of afflictions, and the moſt bitter paſſages of providence, God can certainly bring ſome good to his poor Children; there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo high but his providence is above it; there is nothing ſo low but his providence is beneath it; there is nothing of ſuch an extent, but his providence is able to bound it; and there is nothing ſo confuſed but his providence can order it for his own glory, and his peoples good. O! admire, fear, love, and truſt this great God, that can work all things for the good of his Children.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, By way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, we may hence ſee the reaſon why God doth not prevent
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150135:75"/>the afflictions of his people, and why he doth not remove them ſo ſuddenly as we would have him; it is not for want of love and affection to his people; but becauſe he knows how to bring good to them out of their afflictions. The pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent when he hath a ſmarting Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter applyed to him, cries to the Chyrurgion to take it off, but he doth not take it off as ſoon as the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient would have him, becauſe he knows it works for his good. Would God think you have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Joſeph</hi> to have been ſould into <hi>Egypt,</hi> to have been made a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave, and to have been impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned there, but that he knew how by this abaſement to work his advancement. And do you think God would have ſuffered <hi>David,</hi> after he had annointed him King, to be yet purſued as a partridge upon the mountains, and to be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from one place to another, and brought to ſuch great ſtreights, but that he knew how to work good to him out of all theſe troubles.</p>
            <p>But thirdly, By way of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150135:76"/>this may let us ſee what a vaſt difference there is between the godly, and the wicked, between the condition of the one, and of the other; to the godly, all things, yea the worſt things, even Gods ſevereſt providences, work together for good; but to the wicked, all things, even the beſt things, work toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their hurt, Spirituall good things, and temporall good things, work for their hurt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, All Spirituall good things work for their hurt; as for example, the mercy of God, which is one of the choiceſt Jewels he hath in his Cabanet, this works for the hurt of ungodly men, becauſe it is an occaſion of looſneſs, and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiniſme to them; the grace of God another choice Jewel, works for their hurt, for it is an occaſion of wantoneſs, they turne the grace of God into liciviouſneſs; the patience of God, that is an occaſion of their preſumption; the ordinances they are but poyſon to them; their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme will be but a witneſs of their perjury; the Lords Supper, will
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:150135:76"/>be but as a feal to their damnation; the word of God which to others is a ſavour of life unto life,<note place="margin">Ro. 9.33.</note> unto them it is a favour of death unto death; nay Jeſus Chriſt himſelf to a wicked man is but a ſtumbling ſtone and a rock of offence.</p>
            <p>And as all ſpirituall good things, ſo all temporall good things like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe work for hurt to wicked men; as for example, all providences though they ſeem never ſo ſmiling, and ſucceſſull, do yet tend to the hurt of ungodly men, <hi>The proſperitie of fools ſhall deſtroy them,</hi> Pro. 1.32. ſo likwiſe their riches ſhall be their ruin, their flouriſhing ſhall be their periſhing; their power, their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, their greatneſs, their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, their freinds, their full tables, all theſe ſhall be but as a curſe unto their ſouls;<note place="margin">Mal. 2.2.</note> God curſes his own bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings unto wicked men; As God can turn curſes into bleſſings, where his Children pleaſe him; ſo he can turn bleſſings into curſes to wicked and ungodly men. Had it not been better think you for <hi>Ahithophel,</hi> to have been a very fool rather than
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:150135:77"/>ſuch a great Politician as he was, for his wiſdome was his ruine? Had it not been better for <hi>Abſolom</hi> to have been a deformed creature, than ſo beautifull as he was, for his beauty was his ruine? Had it not been far better for him to have been a kitchin boy than a King, for his power and authoritie was his ruine? Had it not been better for <hi>Haman</hi> to have been the foot-ſtool, rather than ſuch a great favorite in <hi>Ahaſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his Court, for his favour was his ruine; God ſet him in a ſlipperie place to caſt him down to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In a word, all temptations ſhall be for their hurt;<note place="margin">2 Chron. 28.22.</note> all afflictious ſhall be for their hurt. King <hi>Ahas</hi> in the time of his diſtreſſe did treſpaſs yet more againſt the Lord. And all examples, whether of the godly or wicked ſhall be for their hurt; the examples of the godly ſhall make them but fret and rage at them ſo much the more; the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of other wicked men like themſelves, ſhall but infect and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them ſo much the more; death it ſelf ſhall be for their hurt, death ſhall
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:150135:77"/>be as a trap-door, to let them down to the bottomleſs pit of hell, whence they ſhall never, never return. Oh! who would be in a ſtate of unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy and unbelief, in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed and impenitent flate, and ſleep in it one houre? Who would be in the ſtate of the wicked, when all things work for their hurt? That is the third inſtruction.</p>
            <p>The fourth inſtruction by way of information is this; If God can make the ſevereſt of his providences to work for our good, then we have no cauſe to be much troubled at croſſes and afflictions, at tryalls and temptations; we have no cauſe to ſink under the burden of them, but rather to bear them patiently without fainting or fretting; for though at preſent we do not know how they ſhould be forour good, yet God knows how to order them for ourſpirituall advantage here, and for our eternall advantage here after, You will give a Watch-maker leave to take your watch in piecer, becauſe he knows how to put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> together again. So you may give God leave
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:150135:78"/>to break you in your comſorts, and in your own ends and deſigns, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God knows how to ſet you to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether again, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.1. <hi>He hath broken us, and he will heal us, he hath ſmitten and he will bind us up.</hi> When you come at the beginning of the year, and ſee a houſe a building, you ſee nothing but deformity, here a piece of timber, and there ſtones, and in another place rubbiſh; I but come at the end of the year and you ſhall ſee a beautifull fabr ick. We have no cauſe therefore either to fret, or be diſquieted at any paſſage of Gods Providence: In times of preſperity we ſhould not be lifted up; and in times of adverſity we ſhould not be too much caſt down; theſe are the four leſſons by way of inſtruction.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Another Uſe I would make of this Point is, for examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. O! let every one of us call himſelf to account, and ſee whether the providences of God in wayes of ſeverity have wrought for our good yea, or no; hath ſin been preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, hath ſin been diſcovered, hath
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:150135:78"/>it been imbittered, hath it been weakned, if not quite deſtroyed; have our graces been tryed, have they been exerciſed, have we had more faith, more patience, more meekneſs, more humility; have our prayers been more fervent, have our affections been more heavenly, have we got good by every one of our afflictions.</p>
            <p>To perſwade you to this tryall, I will uſe but this one Motive, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member it, and take it for a rule: It is a never failing evedence, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man to be in the ſtate of grace, when he finds every condition drawing him nearer to God, for then it is a manifeſt ſign you are in the number of thoſe that are called, according to his purpoſe, and who love God, and are beloved of God; that is the ſecond Uſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> (and ſo to draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a concluſion) It may ſerve for the unſpeakable conſolation of all thoſe that are good; good Figs, thoſe that are inwardly good, that are impartially good, that are conſtantly good, that fear God, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:150135:79"/>that love God, thoſe who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according to his purpoſe. I tell you my brethren, this is that which may be a ſeaſonable ſupport to your ſpirits in ſad and ſinking times: this very Doctrine may be a heart-ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing cordiall, which were it but rightly reliſhed and digeſted by you, might make your very hearts dance within you for joy. O! that I were but able to convey the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, the ſweetneſs of this cordiall to your hearts, and to my own; cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if you did but ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this, you would not be much troubled at any outward troubles that could befall you; no trouble would be very troubleſome to you. I but ſaies one, alas I am ſlandered and reproached, I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viled, and ſcorned, and am evill ſpoken of, yea though I have not deſerved it; how can this tend to my good? yes, God can by this teach thee to live above the world, above the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and repute of men: it may be thou dideſt reſt too much in the applauſe of man, and dideſt triumph too much in a good name, now God will by this
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:150135:79"/>teach thee to ſeek that honour that comes from him onely, and not that honour that comes from man. It was that which our Saviour laid to the charge of the Phariſees, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. ſaies he, <hi>How can ye believe which receive honour one of another, and ſeek not the honour that cometh from God onely.</hi> And ſaies our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.11, 12. <hi>Bleſſed are you when men ſhall revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evil againſt you falſly for my ſake, rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven.</hi> It is a ſweet ſaying of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſtin, That man that willingly detracts from my good name, he doth againſt his will adde to my Crown.</hi> All the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of men will make our Crown ſo much the heavier. O! but ſaies another, I am very poor; my eſtate and trade is gone; I lie under a great deal of poverty; I want bread for my family, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How can this ever tend for good? yes, it may be God by the poverty of thy eſtate would make thee poor in ſpirit, would make thee humble and baſe in thine
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:150135:80"/>own eyes, it may be God foreſees that if thou ſhouldeſt be rich thou wouledſt be proud, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will keep thee poor that thou maiſt be humble; and 'tis better a thouſand times to be poor in the world and rich in grace, than to be rich in the world and poor in garce.<note place="margin">Jam. 2.5.</note> God chooſeth the poor in the world to be rich in faith; and have other men greater eſtates than thou? it may be they have greater ſnares than thou, are they in higher places than thou? then they are in greater danger of falling than thou; the truth is, the ſoul can better manage a ſtate of adverſitie than aſtate of proſperity; and when the ſoul is under ſome abaſement (pray mark it) it is uſually at a leſſe diſtance from God.</p>
            <p>I but I have a body troubled with many infirmities, with many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, pains and aches, how can this tend to my good? yes, God by this will put thee in mind of thy mortality, that thou haſt a poor tottering Tabernacle, that ere long will drop into duſt, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:150135:80"/>thou muſt ſeek for a houſe on high, a houſe prepared in heaven for thee; and have other ſtronger bodies than thou? it may be they have ſouls leſs weaned from the world than thou; hadſt thou a healthfull body, it may be thy heart would be too much glewed to and ſet upon the world, and this makeſt thee weary of the world, ſo that thou longeſt to be with Jeſus Chriſt, where thou ſhalt be freed from all theſe pains, and ſorrows, and ſufferings; mark it, look wherein we are inferiour unto others in one kind, God ſtill makes it up in ſome other kind.</p>
            <p>I but I am tempted and buffeted with Sathan, and am diſquieted in mind, can this be for my good? yes, the great God of Heaven and earth can order all theſe temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for thy good, as <hi>David</hi> ſaies, Pſal. 118.13. <hi>Thou haſt thruſt ſore at me,</hi> (ſpeaking of <hi>Saul</hi>) <hi>that I might fall, but the Lord helped me;</hi> ſo though Sathan thruſt ſore at thee to wound thee, yet God will ſo order it, that he ſhall wound thy
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:150135:81"/>ſin, but ſhall not hurt thy ſoul. 'Tis an excellent ſaying of Saint <hi>Auſtin;</hi> God (ſaies he) <hi>is ſo good, that he would never ſuffer evil to be in the world, were he not ſo wiſe that he could order all evil for the good of his own people.</hi> Nay God is ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely wiſe, that of poyſon he can make an antidote againſt poyſon: God can order the ſins of his own people for their good, to make them more watchfull, and to be more humble and abaſed in their own eyes, and to long to be where they ſhall ſin no more. This is not an argument for preſumption, but a prop to keep us from deſpair. O! what a comfortable, what a bleſſed condition is this, that whatever the ſtate of Gods people is, yet God can and will turn it all for their good. What tongue of man or Angel can expreſs the conſolation the ſoul might ſind in this Doctrine, were it but rightly reliſhed, and digeſted.</p>
            <p>But one Uſe more, and I will have done; and that is a uſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation; as you have heard ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:150135:81"/>for your comfort, ſo you muſt hear ſomething of dutie alſo.</p>
            <p>If God in the ſevereſt of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences intend our good; then there are four duties that I deſire to propound to you, and I will but propound them, for I cannot preſs them, the time being gone.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Believe this truth.</item>
               <item>2. Apply this truth.</item>
               <item>3. Act according to this truth.</item>
               <item>4. Draw out the ſweetneſs of this truth.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, I would have you believe this truth; that God in all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, though they ſeem never ſo ſtrange, and harſh to you, yet intends your ſpirituall good. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it may ſome ſay; what do you think we are atheiſts; do you think we do not believe the Scripture, when God ſaies all things work for good? I, it may be you believe it, but it is one thing to believe with a notional faith, and another thing to believe with a practicall faith. You read of <hi>the work of faith with power.</hi> 2 Theſ. 1.11.
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:150135:82"/>there are many it may be that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this truth with a notional faith, I but few that believe it with a practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faith; for example, there are none of us but believe we are mortall, that we are poor frail crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that muſt die and drop down to the duſt, we know not how ſoon, we believe this doctrine, with a notionall faith, I but how few be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it with a practical faith, ſo as to prepare for their latter end, to make their whole life a preparation for their dying day; the devils they believe too, they believe that God is a holy and a juſt God, and will render to them according to their deſerts, at that great day when they muſt be judged before all the Angels, and before all the Saints, I but for all this they do not repent; they have a notional faith, I but they have not a practicall faith; ſo it may be you believe this Doctrine, but do you believe it practically, ſo as to make uſe of it, that you are able to ſay, certainly this provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, this affliction, though ſharp, yet tendeth to my ſpirituall good.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:150135:82"/>But Secondly, As I would have you to believe this truth, ſo I would have you apply it unto your own ſouls, that when afflictions come, or troubles come, or ſickneſs comes, when the loſs of a dear husband or wife, or the loſs of a hopefull child, or the loſs of an eſtate comes, when pangs, and pains, and fears, and ſtreights come upon you, you may ſay to every one of them, you are wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, you come with your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, do the work that God ets you about; I know that though for the preſent you are very painfull, yet at the laft you will be very bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, as I have heard the ſtory of a boy in a Ship, when there was ſuch a ſtorm, that threatned the ſinking of the Ship preſently, heſat ſtill, and was not at all troubled; and being asked why he was not troubled, when he ſaw they were in jeopardy of death every minute; O ſaies he, <hi>I know my Father ſits at the ſtern, I know my God hath the diſpoſing of all, and he will order all for good</hi> And O that we could do ſo, this is to apply this Doctrine, and not only to believe it.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:150135:83"/>Thirdly, I would have you act according to your faith; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the utmoſt endeavour of your ſouls be in this, that you may find a ſpirituall advantage by every paſſage of providence, and that every condition may draw you nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to your God. I confeſs this is a hard leſſon to be learnt; but yet there are theſe five means that may help you: I will but name hem:
<list>
                     <item>Firſt, If you would act ſo that every condition may drawy on nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to God, you muſt live not by ſight and ſenſe, but by ſaith; for if you look upon Afflictions with an eye of ſence, you will ſee no good in them at all; but if you look upon them with an eye of faith, then you will ſay ſanctified Affliction is better than unſanctified proſperity; ſanctified ſickneſs better than unſanctified health; and ſanctified poverty, better than unſanctified riches; <hi>For our light affliction,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of Glory;</hi> How did he know this? he tels you in the
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:150135:83"/>next words; <hi>While we look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. 2 Cor. 4.17, 18. as if he ſhould ſay; look not with as eye of fleſh, but with an eye of Faith.</item>
                     <item>And then ſecondly, As a great deal of faith, ſo a great deal of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is required alſo: you muſt not look that the good of affliction ſhould come preſently, (as I told you in one of the limitations) <hi>No af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction for the preſent ſeemeth to be joyous but grievous, nevertheleſs afterwards it yeeldeth the peaceable fruit of righteouſneſs unto them which are exerciſed thereby,</hi> Heb. 12.11. As you muſt exerciſe faith, ſo you muſt be contented to wait alſo.</item>
                     <item>Thirdly, There muſt be a great deal of ſelf-denial too, ſo that you can be content to be croſt of your own wills, that Gods will may be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.</item>
                     <item>Fourthly, You muſt reſolve you will not part with your integrity, though to avoid any affliction; you muſt not chooſe iniquity rather than affliction; but you muſt chooſe
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:150135:84"/>the greateſt affliction, rather than you will commit the leaſt ſin. If you keep your integrity, than this is certain, every affliction will work for your good, and you ſhall find every providence will tend to your ſpirituall advantage in your worſt condition, but on the contrary; if you part with your integrity, you ſhall meet with a curſe in the beſt of your outward conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons here below.</item>
                     <item>And then in the Fift and laſt place, If you would have all thingswork for good, you muſt be much in prayer, Phil. 1.19. ſaies the Apoſtle, (ſpeaking of afflictions) <hi>I know that this ſhall turn to my ſalvation, through your prayer, and the ſupply of the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and this is the third Duty.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And then Fourthly, (And ſo I have done;) Do not onely believe, and apply, and act according to, but labour to draw out the ſweetneſs of this truth, that you may be able to rejoyce in the time of temptation. <hi>My brethren, count it all joy, when you fall into divers temptations,</hi> Jam.
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:150135:84"/>1.2. What to rejoyce in temptations may ſome ſay? if the Apoſtle had ſaid, my brethren, count it all ſorrow when you fall into divers temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he had ſaid ſomething; but count it all joy when you fall into divers temptations; yes, and the Apoſtle knew very well what he ſaid, for he knew that they that ſow moſt in tears, ſhall reap moſt of all in joy, and they that can bear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and temptations, with moſt quiet calm and ſerene ſpirits, they ſhall have the bleſſed fruit of righteouſneſs, though for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they are exerciſed thereby, and God will do them a great deal of good, and will at length bring them to heaven, though by the gates of hell; and 'tis a great deal better to be brought to heaven by the gates of hell, than to be brought to hell by the gates of heaven; and it is better to have our hell here, than to have our hell hereafter, to have a hell of miſery to all eternity: the Lord write every one of theſe things in our hearts, that we may be able to ſpeak
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:150135:85"/>by experience that every one of theſe providences ſhall be for our good. And ſo much ſhall ſuffice for this Text, and for this time.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 10. line 15. r. <hi>deſerts us.</hi> p. 20. l. 18. r. <hi>hear.</hi> p 25. l. 7. r. <hi>of whom.</hi> p. 34. l. 12. r. <hi>others.</hi> p. 41. l. 8. r. <hi>it ſelf.</hi> p. 50. l 9. in ſome Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies r. <hi>had Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150135:85"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
